without saying we're all.
>> good afternoon and welcome
to the MAY 13th, 2025 regular
meeting of the san francisco
board of supervisors.
>> MADAM Clerk, would you
please call the roll?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chen chen present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
presents supervisor engardio
and engardio present supervisor
fielder fielder present
supervisor mahmood mahmood not
present supervisor randleman
mandel men not present
supervisor melgar melgar
present supervisor sartor sadr
present supervisors cheryl
cheryl present and supervisor
walton PRESIDENT Walton present
and supervisor of mahmood
mahmood present MR. PRESIDENT
you have a quorum.
Thank you so much.
The san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the roma to saloni
who are the original
inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula.
As the indigenous stewards of
this land and in accordance
with their traditions the
robertsons alone have never
ceded loss nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside and their traditional
territory.
As guests we recognize that we
benefit from living and working
on their traditional homeland.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the raw
material owning community
and by affirming their
sovereign rights as first
peoples.
Please join me in reciting the
pledge of allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
and to the republic for which
it stands one nation under GOD,
indivisible with liberty
and justice for all.
>> and on behalf of the board
of supervisors I would like to
acknowledge the staff at S.F.
Gov tv and I want to thank
kaleena mendoza who is
recording today's meeting
and making sure our transcripts
are available to the public
online.
>> MADAM Clerk, would you
please call our 2 P.M. Special
order?
>> yes.
The special order at 2 P.M. Is
the appearance by the honorable
mayor daniel lurie.
The mayor MAY address the board
for up to five minutes.
Thank you, mayor lurie.
Thank you.
Welcome.
Good afternoon, supervisor
walton and members of the
board.
I want to start by thanking all
of you.
Our team has spent hours with
many of you in this room
talking about solutions to two
significant challenges facing
our city the behavioral health
crisis and the $800 million
budget deficit.
Thanks to this board's work
and our collaboration we are
tackling both.
Last week at 33 goff we
announced the breaking the
cycle fund a public private
initiative that will deliver
critical resources to transform
san francisco's behavioral
health and homelessness
response.
As we tackle this historic
budget deficit, the fund is
launching with $37.5 million
in private seed funding.
Those resources will help us
move people off the streets
and onto a path to stability.
It will also keep our public
spaces clean and safe
and manage taxpayer dollars
responsibly.
This would not be possible
without your partnership
including your overwhelming
support of the final stage of
emergency ordinance.
Together we are demonstrating
to san franciscans that the
mayor and the board can work
side by side to address the
city's greatest challenges.
That includes the other great
challenge facing our city.
Helping people feel safe on our
streets.
Earlier today I stood with many
of you including supervisors
dorsey and guardiola, mahmood
souder and sheryl to announce a
plan to address our public
safety staffing crisis, our
rebuilding the ranks plan lays
out a clear roadmap to restore
full staffing levels at the spd
and the sheriff's office
includes immediate actions to
relieve pressure on our current
officers along with long term
strategies to build a strong
and sustainable pipeline of
qualified personnel.
these reforms will ensure our
law enforcement agencies have
the support they need to keep
san franciscans safe, reduce
the burden on overworked
officers and implement a more
cost effective sustainable
staffing model.
You all recognize as I do that
our city's comeback depends on
residents and visitors feeling
safe on our streets.
Thank you for supporting this
work and our public safety
professionals.
Meanwhile my budget team many
of whom spent this past weekend
at city hall and other weekends
is working hard to finalize the
budget, find the necessary
savings and protect core city
services.
I am clear eyed about this.
This is hard work but as we've
shown over the past hundred
days we are capable of meeting
big challenges when we work
together.
More to share soon but my top
priority won't change.
Protecting the core san
franciscans core services san
franciscans rely on ensuring
public safety.
Addressing the homelessness
and addiction crisis
and bringing our economy back.
I want to thank you all for
your partnership in advancing
those goals and I look forward
to continuing that work.
>> thank you, mayor lurie.
MADAM Clerk, would you please
call the first topic?
>> yes, the first topic
submitted by the district seven
supervisor supervisor myrna
melgar is vision zero.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Hello, mayor.
thank you for being here,
mayor.
In 2014 our city made a promise
to end traffic deaths by 2024.
It was an initiative that was
spearheaded by my predecessor,
district seven supervisor
norman yee also PRESIDENT Of
the board.
He himself was a victim, a
survivor of traffic violence
which left him disabled for
almost a year.
He had to learn how to walk
again.
His wife who was a teacher who
was a teacher at the time had
to take time off of work to
care for him.
>> unfortunate early this
promise in our actions leading
up to it or after it have not
really yielded the results that
we intended.
The this last year we saw 39
people lose their lives
and many more injuries.
These deaths and the tens of
thousands of additional crashes
that took place on our streets
have cost san francisco
billions of dollars.
Last week we you know, had a
rally where we talked about a
budget and legislative
analyst's report that estimated
the costs at $2.5 billion over
the last five years.
>> and you know, our street
safety budget is a very small
portion of the mta budget
overall.
You have championed public
safety and security and also
economic recovery on our
streets and this is very much
part of public safety.
So today my question is what
commitments and investments do
you intend to make in order to
renew our goal of zero deaths
and establish the next
iteration of a vision zero
policy for us?
>> thank you.
Supervisor.
As I said a minute ago, public
safety is my top priority and I
appreciate the opportunity to
partner with many of you
in this room on that work.
And I want to be crystal clear
I believe that traffic safety
is public safety.
I want san franciscans to feel
safe on our streets.
That means feeling safe from
any threat.
But when we talk about vision
zero zero, we're not just
talking about traffic safety.
We're talking about the kind of
city that we want to be.
From day one my administration
has focused on restoring safety
and accountability in san
francisco.
And I believe they're at the
core of making our streets
safer for everyone.
Let's start with enforcement.
You've heard the public, you've
seen the data and when people
engage in reckless driving flee
from law enforcement or
endanger lies behind the wheel
,they must be held
accountable.
That's how we restore order
and protect our communities.
And I believe we need more
officers on our streets to
enforce the rules of the road
because traffic laws only work
when they're enforced.
Supervisor mandel hearings made
that clear and that's why many
of us stood together this
morning to announce the
rebuilding the ranks
and address our speed and share
of staffing crisis head on.
We're also using and leading
the state in advanced
technology to enforce safe
streets.
Our first in the state
automated speed cameras have
been operating in a no fee
warning period to help
reinforce safe driving behavior
before enforcement and fees
begin.
And the S.F. Mta has led the
way in advancing safe street
designs redesigns and just a
couple of weeks ago supervisor
you walton you and I cut the
ribbon on the potrero gateway a
transformative streetscape
projected project that widened
sidewalks, protected bike lanes
and turned a dangerous
intersection into a safer, more
welcoming passageway from
potrero hill to the mission.
We're going to keep doing
whatever it takes to keep our
residents and visitors safe
and that means using all the
tools and our vision zero
toolbox.
So I appreciate the question.
Supervisor melgar and I thank
you for giving me the
opportunity to talk and I look
forward to partnering with you
and the rest of the board on
this issue going forward.
>> thank you.
Supervisor melgar, do you have
a follow up question?
I do not thank you.
>> thank you so much,
mayor lurie, you MAY ask a
question of supervisor melgar
or any of my other colleagues.
>> good.
And thank you very much.
I appreciate you.
thank you so much.
MR. Mayor.
>> with that said and no
question, MADAM Clerk, this
concludes our mayoral
discussion.
>> thank you for joining us.
Mayor MADAM Clerk, you have
communications for us today.
>> did you.
>> my apologies.
I did not see your name on the
roster supervisor dorsey.
No problem.
This is this isn't mostly I
just wanted to express on
behalf of the board of
supervisors our welcome to the
students of the how san
francisco government works
civics class led by michael
adams from my district and we
just always want to express our
appreciation to the people who
are interested in the work that
we do here so welcome, welcome
.
It's MADAM Clerk we have in the
communique since this
afternoon.
>> yes.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
My office is in receipt of a
memo dated APRIL 29th, 2025
from PRESIDENT Mandel men's
office stating his absence from
today's meeting and his request
to be excused from attendance.
Additionally, pursuant to board
rule 4.8 entitled PRESIDENT Pro
tem PRESIDENT Men has appointed
supervisor sherman walton to
perform the duties as the
presiding officer for today's
meeting.
Therefore it is customary to
refer to a PRESIDENT Pro tem as
MR. PRESIDENT or PRESIDENT
Walton for the remainder of the
meeting.
>> to our communication the san
francisco board of supervisors
welcomes you to attend this
meeting in the board's
legislative chamber here
in city hall second floor room
250 or you MAY watch the
proceeding on S.F. Gov't tv's
channel 26 or view the
livestream at ww u w dot s f g
of t v.Org if you have public
comment you'd like to submit
in writing send an email to be
offset as f gov.Org or use the
postal service and address your
envelope to the san francisco
board of supervisors the number
one DR. Carlton b goodlatte
place city hall room 244 san
francisco, california 94102.
>> to make a reasonable
accommodation request under the
americans with disabilities act
or to request language
assistance contact the clerk's
office two business days
in advance by calling and I'll
give you the number
(415) 554-5184.
Thank you, members thank you,
MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you so much, MADAM
Clerk and per his request, MAY
I have a motion to excuse
PRESIDENT MADAM min from
attending today's meeting?
Motion made by supervisor
cheryl seconded by supervisor
chin MADAM Clerk on that motion
on the motion to excused
supervisor from board PRESIDENT
Rafael mandel and from today's
meeting supervisor fielder
fielder eyes supervisor mahmood
mahmood eyes supervisor melgar
melgar eyes supervisor sadr
sadr eyes supervisor cheryl
cheryl I supervise her walton I
walton eyes supervisor chin
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
i supervisor dorsey dorsey I
and supervisor engardio
and engardio I there are ten
eyes thank you without
objection PRESIDENT MADAM is
excused from today's meeting
MADAM Clerk we're going to go
to approval of the minutes
and today we are approving the
meeting minutes from our APRIL
eighth 2025 regular board
meeting.
Any changes or any request from
colleagues?
>> I don't see any so I will
entertain a motion to approve
the minutes from the APRIL 8th
meeting made by supervisor
cheryl seconded by supervisor
melgar, MADAM Clerk on the
motion on the motion to approve
the APRIL 8th, 2025 meeting
minutes as presented supervisor
fielder fielder eyes supervisor
mahmood mahmood eyes supervisor
melgar melgar eyes supervisor
sadr sadr eyes supervisor
cheryl cheryl eyes supervisor
walton eye walton eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eye
and supervisor engardio
and engardio eye there are ten
eyes without objection the
minutes will be approved after
public comment as presented
MADAM Clerk let's go to our
consent agenda items two
through five items two through
five are on consent.
>> these items are considered
to be routine.
If a member objects an item MAY
be removed and considered
separately.
>> thank you.
I don't see anyone on the
roster to sever any items or
have any objections so without
objection we'll take this
ordinance.
>> same house, same call MADAM
Clerk, please call item number
six regular agenda unfinished
business item six this is an
ordinance to appropriate
approximately 5.4 million from
the general reserve
and approximately 311,000 of
boarding of prisoners revenue
and to appropriate
approximately 86.3 million from
salaries mandatory fringe
benefits vehicles, programmatic
projects, capital renewal
projects and building
and structure improvement
projects and to appropriate
approximately 61 million to
overtime in the police
department and 30 million to
overtime in the sheriff's
department in order to support
the department's projected
increases in overtime
and approximately 1 million to
building and structure
improvement projects
and building repair in the
sheriff's department.
>> thank you so much and I
don't see anyone on the roster,
MADAM Clerk so would you please
call the roll on this item on
item six supervisor fielder
fielder no.
Supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl eyes
supervisor walton no walton no
supervisor chan chan eyes
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
and supervisor ryan gaudio
and gaudio I there are eight
eyes and two nose with
supervisors fielder and walton
voting no thank you.
>> this ordinance is finally
passed with an 8 to 2 vote with
supervisors fielder and myself
voting no and just a correction
we actually have hymie ashbury
from S.F. Go tv making sure
that our meeting is televised
and publicized today so
correction on my earlier
statement MADAM Clerk would you
please call item number seven?
>> thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
Item seven this is a resolution
to retroactively authorize the
acceptance and expenditure of
state transportation
development act article three
pedestrian and bicycle project
funding by the san francisco
public works from the
metropolitan transfer station
commission for fiscal year 2021
2223, 2023 and 24 in the amount
of approximately 1.36 million
for the term of JULY 1st 2024
through JUNE 30th 2027.
Thank you MADAM Clerk would you
please call the roll on item
number seven and item seven
supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton I walton I
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
and supervisor engardio
and engardio either or tonight
thank you this resolution is
adopted MADAM Clerk please call
item number eight item eight
resolution to approve an
agreement for the sale of an
approximate 5000 449,000 square
foot vacant lot of city
property to the adjacent
property owner bayview
mackinnon llc for approximately
375,000 and to find the city's
property to be exempt surplus
land under the california
government code.
>> thank you.
Seeing no one on the roster we
will take this item.
>> same house, same call MADAM
Clerk would you please call
items nine and ten together?
Item nine and ten are two
resolutions that approve
and authorize the director of
property to execute lease
agreements with the bayview
plaza llc for space located at
30 801 third street.
Item nine is a resolution on
behalf of the human services
agency for a three year term
with one five year option to
extend for 16,000ft2 of space
which includes seats, two
suites, 200 205, 210 220 230
235.
240 and 250 at an annual base
rent of approximately 526,000
with no annual rent increases.
And item ten this resolution is
on behalf of the department of
public health for a five year
term with two five year options
to extend through NOVEMBER 30th
2029 with bayview plaza llc for
suite 400 at a base rent of
approximately 489,000 per year
with no annual rent increases.
>> thank you and seeing no one
on the roster we will take
these items same house, same
call and without objection
these resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call item
number 11.
Item 11 this is a resolution to
approve the second modification
to a contract with hallmark
aviation services lp for
airport information and guest
assistance services and with a
one year extension for a total
term of JULY 1st 2024 through
JUNE 30th 2026 and to increase
the contract amount by 10.7
million for a new contract
amount of approximately 20
million.
>> thank you.
Seeing no one on the roster we
will take this item.
Same house, same car and the
resolution is adopted without
objection MADAM Clerk please
call items 12 and 13 together
items 12 and 13 are two
resolutions that provide
retroactive authorization to
accept and expend monetary
gifts from epic systems
corporation and for the
department of public health to
support federally qualified
health centers and their
underserved patient populations
for the duration of JULY 1st
2023 through JUNE 30th 2025.
Item 12 is for 2021 epic for
federally qualified health
centers in the amount of
204,000 and item 13 is for t22
safety net in the amount of
115,000 thank you MADAM Clerk.
I don't see anyone on the
roster so we will take these
resolutions same house, same
call and without objection
these resolutions are adopted.
MADAM Clerk please call item
number 14 item 14 this is a
resolution to approve the
second amendment to the grant
agreement between homeless
prenatal program and the
department of homelessness
and support of housing to
provide rapid rehousing for
families through the support of
housing assistance
and readiness efforts program
to extend the term by four
years through JUNE 30th 2029
and to increase the agreement
by approximately 13.8 million
for a new total amount of
approximate only 22.6 million.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk.
Seeing no one on the roster we
will take this item same
health, same call and without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
number 15 item 15 this is a
resolution to authorize the
office of the assessor recorder
to execute the second amendment
of the mou.
The memorandum of understanding
with the california elect
electronic recording
transaction network authority
for ab 578 electronic records
ation implementation for
recommendation of digitized
electronic records and certain
digital electronic records to
update the annual costs per
title based on the tier pricing
plan and to extend the existing
mou term by 13 years for a
total duration of 19 years
through JANUARY 10th 2035.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk.
Seeing no one on the roster we
will take this item same house,
same call and this resolution
is adopted without objection
MADAM Clerk please call item
number 16 item 16 this is a
motion to approve the mayor's
nomination for the appointment
of dan callimachi to the
building inspection commission
term ending JULY 1st, 2027.
Thank you.
And seeing no one on the roster
we would take this item same
house, same call without
objection this motion is
approved MADAM Clerk please
call item 17 item 17 this is a
motion to appoint ted jackson
and jane redmond to the in-home
supportive services public
authority terms ending MARCH
1st, 2028.
>> thank you.
Seeing no one on the roster we
will take this item same house,
same call.
And without objection this
motion is approved.
>> MADAM Clerk we are still a
little early so let's go to
roll call for introductions for
roll call for introductions.
>> the first member to
introduce new business is
supervisor fielder.
>> thank you so much.
I'm actually going to save my
introduction as remarks for the
commendations because they're
related so I'll submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor fielder supervisor
mark mark.
>> colleagues today I'm excited
to introduce two resolutions to
honor DR. Amos c brown with a
street renaming of two blocks
off pier street alongside third
baptist church which DR. Brown
has led for nearly 50 years.
>> ahead of his retirement the
summer the first resolution is
for a commemorative street
renaming while the other
commences the more time
consuming public works
surveying and outreach process
required for the official
street renaming process.
>> I've been so fortunate to
have the opportunity to sit
with DR. Brown and learn from
him about the history of the
fillmore and western asian
communities.
Anyone who's met with DR. Brown
knows that he's a strong willed
advocate unafraid to push back
against the broken elements of
our society in service to
justice, equality and humanity
.
>> he's quick to point out the
injustices in the city
and society generally has
taught me so much about public
service and how to incorporate
justice into everything that I
do.
He worked directly with civil
rights legends like medgar
evers, DR. Martin luther king
jr and has helped pass their
wisdom, perspective and sense
of conviction and to future
generations.
>> the impact of DR. Brown's
career of leadership advocacy
and service in san francisco
cannot be understated.
>> since his appointment as
senior pastor at third baptist
church in 1976, he's led with a
powerful vision around
community and service
especially for the younger
generation.
>> under DR. Brown's
leadership, the church has
worked with the congregation
emanuel on creating the back on
track afterschool program
created with the tennessee
academy of music to encourage
the next generation of
performers and songwriters
and the freedom school summer
program for underprivileged
youth.
>> DR. Brown has also been a
longtime chair of the local
chapter of the naacp.
>> he was a former member of
this body as well.
>> I believe if you sit, sat
and change supervisor chauncey
and also former member of the
city college as well as stated
served as our state as vice
chair of the california
reparations task force even
with all he's done locally, DR.
Brown's reach has been global.
He raised funds in response to
crises across africa and helped
lead efforts to resettle
refugees from ethiopia
and eritrea right here in the
western tradition.
DR. Brown and his wife jane
even hosted refugees in their
home.
>> it has been powerful to hear
from the ethiopian and eritrean
community in this district but
how grateful they are for his
efforts.
DR. Brown is retiring later
this summer from third baptist
and the street renaming will be
a fitting honor for his
incredible legacy as a civil
rights icon and as an outspoken
advocate for the black
community in san francisco.
Thank you colleagues for your
support.
Second time.
Second today I'm also proud to
forward a resolution with the
mayor.
>> the represents a new chapter
for kezar stadium and for how
we think about sports, public
space and community investment
in san francisco.
>> this resolution authorizes a
long term permit between the
recreation and parks department
and golden city football club,
a new professional soccer team
that will soon call keyser home
.
This is about more than just a
new team.
Golden city football club has
made it clear that they want to
be a part of the community not
just playing it from day one.
They've been focused on
building meaningful
partnerships with local
merchants, investing in public
improvements that benefit all
users of keyser and ensure that
neighborhood character
and access are preserved.
This is a public private
partnership that respects the
legacy of kezar while helping
write its future and it brings
new energy, new fans and new
opportunities for small
businesses and the haight
in our sunset and beyond.
>> as we prepare san francisco
to play a role in the global
spotlight of the 2026 world
cup, this is a chance to show
how professional sports can be
done differently grounded
in equity, community and care
for public space.
>> I want to thank mayor leary
rec and park city fc and the
many local stakeholders have
shaped this vision.
And I also want to thank my
colleagues supervisor randleman
and melgar for their early
support on an exciting project
for our city.
>> the rest I submit thank you.
Supervisor mahmood given that
it's not yet 230 MR. PRESIDENT
will go to the next supervisor.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Supervisor melgar.
>> okay.
Mine is a little bit long so.
>> okay, colleagues.
In light of our impending
rezoning discussions, I'd like
to share with you about a
package of legislation.
>> some of them are drafting
proposals or drafting requests.
Some of them are legislation
that I've been working on for
many months that address some
of the concerns that we have
heard from folks regarding the
package, the zoning proposal,
the family zoning proposal.
Some of them address the need
for affordable housing on the
west side.
Address tenant displacement
and mitigation of small
businesses and disruption while
we are conferring some value to
the parcels that are getting up
zoning.
We also need to make sure that
for the future we plan out for
affordability and stability for
our communities as we are
concurrently working on a
regional housing measure
in future bonds.
We are exploring a few ideas
with the city attorney to
increase funding for affordable
housing and we want to make
sure that we meet our
obligations to the housing
element.
So these are the proposals that
we will be making.
The first is the creation of an
enhanced infrastructure
financing district for the west
side to eventually provide
funding for affordable housing
development on the west side,
an area of the city that has
seen very little of that for
decades.
Along with that we are
proposing some sebel position
to tenants when facing rent,
evictions and displacement due
to construction.
We are we've also heard from
the small business community
that they are deeply concerned
at that construction would mean
displacement for them because
they lack the tenant
protections that residential
tenants have.
So we are proposing the
creation of a fund to help with
relocation and also to mitigate
any loss of foot traffic due to
construction.
And last but not least I am
also pursuing creating a
alternative to meeting section
415 obligations to affordable
housing by having developers
voluntarily choose up rent
control instead of an
affordable housing fee or a bmr
requirement.
So all of these things at will
come to the lady's a
transportation committee.
We are also honoring the
requests of the planning
department to hold an
informational hearing for the
up zoning proposal at the land
use and transportation
committee to provide yet
another avenue for people to
weigh in on this very important
policy change in our city.
I am also introducing on behalf
of the planning department a
resolution updating the
priority conservation areas for
the metropolitan transportation
commission which the board last
did in 2015.
In was most recently updated
in 2019.
>> priority conservation areas
are designated geographic areas
nominated by local
jurisdictions and recognized by
our regional bodies to support
conservation, resilience
and sustainability goals.
>> the process is an
opportunity for the city to
expand these areas to support
recreation, neighborhood
greening, climate adaptation
and specific projects within
designated pcas are also
eligible for funding from the
metropolitan transportation
commission.
For the pc grant program which
helps local government park
districts utility district
and other agencies acquire or
enhance designee debt areas.
>> and lastly I am introducing
a resolution today recognizing
bike to wherever day which will
be on MAY 15th a couple of days
from now.
It is a regional celebration of
bicycling which as you all know
is something that I love to do
as well as supervisor dorsey.
This isn't just about biking to
work.
It's also about empowering san
franciscans to use bicycles
wherever they go whether it's
the grocery store, school work
just wherever and to enjoy our
beautiful city from two wheels.
>> it aligns with our broader
environmental equity goals.
It encourages low cost zero
emission mobility in a city
where car ownership is not
accessible or desirable to many
people.
San francisco is taking
concrete steps to become a more
bike friendly city.
>> we've recently launched the
biking and rolling plan and we
have planned upgrades to over
385 route segments and the goal
to connect at least 10% of city
streets with bike lanes.
We're working towards a city
where everyone lives within a
quarter mile of a safe
and comfortable bike ride.
this thursday, MAY 15th will
see over 300 energizer stations
across the bay area including
here in san francisco where
people can pick up a
commemorative tote.
>> hydrate connect with fellow
cyclists, celebrate how far
we've come and I encourage
everyone to take part in this
celebration.
Dust off your bike.
Try a new route or just take a
spin around the block with that
colleague's I respectfully
request your support for this
resolution recognizing MAY 15th
as bike to wherever de san
francisco and the rest I submit
.
>> thank you supervisor melgar
back to you MR. PRESIDENT.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Would you please call our 230
special commendation?
>> yes.
It is now time for the
recognition of commendations
for meritorious service to the
city and county of san
francisco.
>> colleagues today we have
four special commendations from
districts 11, nine, seven
and four and we will go in that
order.
>> so we will start with
supervisor chin.
Thank you, PRESIDENT Colleagues
good afternoon.
Today it it's my great honor to
commend principal lisa siddall,
a principal sitter what you
want to come and send by the
post?
Yes.
After 40 years of dedication
that is that is well deserved
and I along with my colleagues
supervisor magara we are here
to recognize her ground
breaking career in pioneering
chinese immersion education
and to celebrate her upcoming
retirement.
>> principal zero it's a
district 11 resident who for
the last 40 years has shown
incredible dedication to our
students in the room and has
championed the power of
language and education.
>> she pioneered a chinese
chinese language immersion
in 1984 before it was offer of
value in public schools and a
debt and a decade later in 1995
she found the alex wong you
alternative school the first
ever chinese immersion public
school in the country.
Congratulations ben and then
principal yee has been the
principal there for the last 30
years leading the school
through many adventures
and achievements language
immersion is an amazing
innovative learning strategy.
>> it helps students develop
cognitive abilities, build
wider shows or connections
and increase cultural knowledge
which is especially important
in a multicultural city like
san francisco.
>> language immersion also
makes our city safer by
fostering, by fostering
classroom skill communities to
communicate and build trust
and by encouraging young people
to become engaged global
citizens.
Chinese language immersion is
especially important in san
francisco a city with robust
chinese history and population.
This aapi heritage month we
highlight the importance of the
chinese language in sustaining
chinese heritage principal
zito's leadership is well
recognized in 2012 she received
the terrill h.
Bao award for outstanding
leadership from the U.S.
Department of education
and award given to only a few
of principals each year under
her leadership, alice fong
school also received many
crowns over the years as the
national blue ribbon school
california distinguished school
and the california go ribbon
school.
>> this awards commemorate the
school's explanatory academic
achievements and their ability
to close the achievement gap.
Principal szeto we honor your
hard work, your faith to your
vision and the meaningful
impact that you MAY on the city
you are an inspiration.
Congratulations on your
retirement and I also want to
say if you were in cantonese as
you led by example to begin
in cantonese see on hon you see
that saw your chin double sweep
guys I want you to see an
bakery octagon double yolk tie
for wong ming sindhi and tong
soo civil generally hak always
say something young poplin soo
young getting way more we see
fong he chin they beosound
dissect termites see white
white house on top endorsing
don't tell my hmong zone get
more thai pork daal yet though
you know yet I guess our
willingness our thoughts L.A.
Highly tech domingue youtz I
you totally I something a pinch
on your being yao zi that jin
hong file now I would like to
turn it over to my colleague
supervisor malka for her
remarks.
>> thank you, buzzy okay.
Okay.
Thank you.
I would never thank you.
>> thank you supervisor chen
and welcome to alice fong.
You students, staff
and families here today to
share this special moment with
us.
I'm very proud to have alice
for you in at district seven
principal the lsc you know I'm
so fond of you your legacy has
really left an impact on san
francisco.
I think you are one of the best
educational leaders in our city
.
You have served and shaped many
generations of san franciscans
and continue to live on
in every young person you have
worked with, in every educator
you have mentored every young
person including as you know,
members of my own family,
students from past and present
will always remember your
kindness but also your
firmness.
You embody that concept of a
warm demander.
You definitely hold everyone to
a high standard high
expectation and it shows
because graduates from alice
fong you go off did you
increase edible things are
ready for this new global ized
bilingual trilingual world that
we live in and I am so proud of
your legacy as such at today
this board of supervisors will
be voting on a resolution
declaring MAY 18th as liana
sito day in the city and county
of san francisco.
we don't do this for everyone
but we are recognizing your
pioneer leadership.
It deserves a day of
recognition.
It has been an honor to work
with you all these years with
the alice fong you community
and I hope you get to enjoy a
lovely retirement with lots of
rest and joy in your daily
life.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
>> wow.
>> principal sito you have the
floor.
Well, thank you so much.
It is a bit overwhelmed.
>> PRESIDENT Walton, san
francisco board of supervisors
on their guests and the
citizens of this world class
city.
>> let's give ourselves a big
hand.
>> yes, I am lee aniceto.
>> oh, the proud principal of
alice fong.
Your school the nation's first
chinese immersion school.
>> first of all, thank you,
supervisor chen and supervisor
melgar for your kind kind words
.
I accept this honor with
humility as an immigrant, a
first generation chinese
american, I step on the
shoulders of many unsung asian
american heroes and heroes who
came before me.
>> I would like to highlight
today in particular MISS Alice
fong yu who is a namesake of my
school MISS U was born in a
small town of washington,
california in 1905 despite
racial discrimination and being
told she could not teach
in public schools because she
was ethnically chinese, she
pursued her dream to become a
teacher.
She was accepted finally in the
teacher's college because she
said she would go back quote
unquote to china.
>> she was born in america
and she did accept all she was
hired became the first
chinese-american teacher in san
francisco at the commodore
stockton school now called
gordon j.
>> lao.
>> her story of oh for coming
discrimination and obstacles
inspires generation of asian
american in our continue work
to advocate for equity
and access for the asian
american community, I want to
just leave you with a chinese
proverb that inspires me deal
young some teach you highly
more things literally
translated as if you have
perseverance and grit you can
grind an iron ore into a needle
.
It's a metaphor for
highlighting the value,
patience and hard work
in overcoming obstacles the
asian american experience the
chinese american stories are
often hidden and overshadowed
told the asian community is
diverse, multifaceted
and complex.
>> our stories span across the
globe.
Our lives intertwine and asian
americans certainly have come
and make progress and come a
long way.
But the work continues.
>> so happy asian american
pacific islander month to
everyone.
>> thank you very much.
>> thank you for your answer.
Congratulations
.
And can I say can I give can we
give my wonderful students a
big round?
>> of course.
Congratulations.
This is so supervisor fielder.
>> thanks so much.
So today I want to invite up to
the podium santiago and irene
lopez.
>> I would like to honor a
massive source of pride for
district nine the mission's
very own alpha elite the
football club which is which is
a local soccer and football
club that represents the best
of not only san francisco but
also the latino and working
class community of port elite
though is more than a soccer
team it is a living testament
to community resilience and the
beautiful game.
I want to thank head coach
and general manager santiago
lopez and irene lopez, the club
manager who are joining us
today.
Founded in 1985 by the late
salvador don chava lopez
vallejo's football club emerged
from humble beginnings rising
through the ranks of the san
francisco soccer football
league to claim national glory
by winning the U.S. Open cup
in 1993 under the name club
deportivo mexico.
That 1993 victory has forever
cemented their name in american
soccer history and laid the
foundation for decades of
grassroots excellence.
>> the trophy still sits inside
the bar on 24th and mission a
physical reminder of what's
possible for a team built from
and for its community.
For four decades this family
run club has been woven into
the mission's cultural fabric
reflecting the hard work
and pride of san francisco's
latino community.
The team's players are local
residents bouncing day jobs
with their passion for soccer.
And yet they have stunned the
soccer world by beating
professional opponents over the
years.
The current team is led by head
coach and general manager
santiago lopez who carries
forward his father's vision
with passion and dedication
and as well as irene lopez, the
club manager who plays an
integral role in the team's
operations.
The two of them are integral to
the team's success
and continuing the team's
historic legacy of elite.
>> those recent success
includes remarkable
performances as in the U.S.
Open cup making it to the third
round in each of the last two
years in 2020 for they stunned
the soccer community by
defeating mls portland timbers
with a21 victory and then
narrowly fell to useless
oakland roots in a hard fought
match.
>> just this year alfaro later
made further history as they
overcame real monarchs sc 321
after extra time and also
secured a 2 to 1 victory
against monterey bay fc before
a tough loss to sacramento
republic in a third round.
>> I'm not only offering a
commendations for a little
today I'm also proud to share
that I am introducing a
resolution to honor
and congratulate vallejo I've
seen for their remarkable run
in the U.S. Open cup
and declare MAY 22nd.
As for a lethal day in the city
and county of san francisco.
>> I want to thank my early co
sponsors supervisors chen
melgar and walton.
>> thank you again to alpha
elite iv c for continuing to
embody the spirit of the
mission remaining deeply rooted
in the community.
We are grateful for the pride
and inspiration that finally
brings to our city and the
unwavering commitment to
excellence shown both on
and off the field.
And a special thanks to my
former legislative aide preston
kilgore for his love of soccer
and his six years of service
in city hall.
>> I am now going to hand it
over to supervisor chen who is
also going to share some
remarks.
>> great.
Thank you supervisor fielder
for celebrating and recognizing
our fa aledo soccer club.
>> your team plays at the
ballpark sponsor stadium
bringing so much pride to
district 11.
Thank you.
Their skew and commitment to
the sport is not only
impressive but serves as the
beacon for many young soccer
player in my district and city
y.
>> through hard work
and dedication and and despite
of lack of resources they you
your team beat the professional
teams across the country.
Amazing.
Thank you.
You are the soccer players
example exemplify the san
francisco spirit throughout
your own resilience passion
and diversity.
>> and I'm so proud to see a
local homegrown team sassy
and fresh in the way that you
all have and I look forward to
watching your legacy
and congratulations again.
>> thank you.
You have the floor.
Thank you.
Thank you, supervisor fielder
for this commendation.
And all the supervisors here
in san francisco that are here
today and congratulations to
everyone here for their
commendations.
I gratefully accept this
commendation on behalf of all
is all things fa little my
father salvador lopez.
He showed me the importance of
being part of a team.
And in fact our little soccer
club is one great example of
this.
And for ito not only is food
but it's also a soccer team.
It's an example of hard work
and the consistency that it
takes to still be around.
And most importantly to stay at
team that can compete.
>> and today that would not be
possible without my brother
santiago lopez, the coach of
alfaro lito.
He has been hard working,
bettering himself while
building a team of coaches
and players that are up to the
challenge.
Alfaro little will not be the
team that it is without the
players thinks.
Thanks to the players from the
past and present without their
effort and support we will not
be able to call ourselves a
team.
They give me a mini heart
attacks every time they play
especially on the ones in the
us open.
>> every season is different
and challenging and unknown.
But one thing has always been
the same.
We play to win every little
soccer club has been around
since the early 80s playing
in balboa and being part of the
mission district which is a
long time.
But that does not matter to us
as a team.
And finally we will try to
continue this tradition as long
as possible and continue to
represent my father the mission
district community in san
francisco.
Not only with food but with
soccer.
>> thank you very much.
>> we brought you a gift of the
2025 open cup roster.
They're all signed
and especially for you
and congratulations again.
Supervise as are melgar.
>> thank you so much.
PRESIDENT Walton.
And could phebe lee please come
up along with her companion
right now commissioner hanley
chan.
Okay.
Thank you for being here with
us.
>> colleagues, welcome phebe
and thank you commissioner chan
for escorting her
and colleagues.
Today I have the distinct honor
of commanding a pillar of san
francisco's asian-american
community feebly.
>> I am so proud she's also a
district seven resident and I
thank you commissioner chan for
being here with us today.
Also phebe lee is a very
talented martial artist
storyteller and the eldest
sister of bruce lee who is not
only an international star but
was born right here at chinese
hospital in san francisco.
>> for the past few decades,
MS..
Lee has devoted her time to
sharing the incredible story of
herself and her family.
MR. Lee's father was one of the
leading cantonese opera singers
and film actors of his day
and her mother was a fixture of
hong kong high society.
Her brother was perhaps the
most iconic martial artist of
all time.
>> MS..
Lee's commitment to sharing her
family's stories remind us of
the hard work, the perseverance
and the successes of
asian-american aunts in san
francisco and throughout the
country.
MS..
Lee has spent her life building
bridges between diverse
communities and sharing her
culture and her story.
Her work has inspired future
generations of san franciscans
and for that we should all be
immensely grateful.
mossley continues to be such an
inspiration and you seem
ageless and boundless with
energy.
I remember distinctly how you
showed me some of your graceful
martial arts moves last time
that we saw each other and had
dinner.
I just want to thank you for
always reminding those around
you about the power of movement
and reflection.
Thank you, phoebe.
I know that you don't want to
say remarks.
I'm grateful that you're here
and that we are able to commend
you in your contributions to
the life of san francisco
today.
And I am honored that you're
here with us and really soaring
on more mobile by jungle.
So diamond told the young talk
about her family talking about
bruce lee robert robert's is
in hong kong right now and to
sister.
But they passed away.
And of course his dad was a
famous opera singer and the new
premier opera.
>> that's why I believe he was
born here.
I also want to singapore I want
to go around the world to a
premier opera.
Yeah, I my father to two
daughters one knows me one
endlessly as they're studying
unity.
I studied in taiwan.
That's why I speak mandarin
and cantonese some of my
english you know and to get to
know all my family all gone.
Only me in university.
Yeah.
And give me I'm a I'm I'm glad
to be here today.
Thank you.
I just want to thank the board
supervisor for recognizing her.
>> bruce lee, of course is a
icon not only to san francisco
but to the world.
It broke a lot of barriers for
the asian-american community.
>> thank you.
Thank you and congratulations
to.
>> congratulations again.
And last but not least we have
district four supervisor
joellen gaudio.
>> thank you class gabriela gui
and lily wang to step forward
to the podium please.
>> colleagues, today I'm
honoring one of our most
important partners in serving
the chinese-american community
in the sunset wami school.
Wami is the first bilingual
preschool in san francisco.
It was founded in 1974, the
same year that the supreme
court ruled in a landmark case
that failing to provide
language accommodations to
non-english speaking students
violated the civil rights act
of 1964.
The lao v nichols ruling
established the legal
foundation for bilingual
education in america.
While my school was founded
in response to this victory,
while its founders were
determined to create an
educational environment where
chinese-american children could
thrive in both cultures
and languages rather than being
forced to choose between them
51 years later, waimea has
built multiple generations of
trust with parents
and neighbors.
Executive director ben wang has
led waimea for the past decade,
expanding its reach with the
full support of board PRESIDENT
Gabriela gui under their
leadership, waimea has evolved
into an umbrella organization
for the youth and family
network of district four
working closely with other
trusted partners such as gum
moon, women's residents
and sunset youth services.
During the covid pandemic,
waimea demonstrated its
community commitment by opening
emergency child care centers
and hosting testing sites when
they were desperately needed.
And in 2021 wom stepped up to
lead the newly created sunset
chinese cultural district, the
first cultural district on the
west side.
We also have to acknowledge
lily wong y mayes director of
community engagement.
It was lily's job to make the
sunset chinese cultural
district come to life
and become a pioneering force
in community engagement.
>> the culture district honors
old traditions like autoimmune
festival and helps create new
traditions like the sunset
night market with lily's
leadership.
The cultural district has made
the sunset a better place to
live by creating beautiful
murals that celebrate the
sunsets cultural diversity.
She also led the creation of a
strategy report that documents
everything the sunset needs to
thrive from housing to economic
sustainability.
Together kwami and the sunset
chinese cultural district
ensure that our
chinese-american community has
both strong educational
foundations and vibrant
cultural connections.
They bridge generations,
preserve heritage and create
spaces where community members
can fully express their
identities.
So I'd like to invite y MAY
board PRESIDENT Gabrielle
aguiar to speak on behalf of my
school followed by lily wang
with the sunset chinese
cultural district.
>> thank you supervisor
and guardian.
Hi everybody.
I am gabby guy wu.
Thank you.
Today for presenting our award.
Again, thank you.
Supervising engardio and the
board of supervisors the board
of directors for this
incredible honor during aapi
heritage month.
On behalf of guam and the
sunset chinese cultural
district we are deeply grateful
for this recognition of our
work in preserving
and celebrating aapi culture
in district four one as one of
the first chinese bilingual
preschool in california started
with just seven kids in the
living room of one of our
founders, judge lillian sings
living room two today proudly
serving over 500 youth
and families on a daily basis.
As a parent and resident of
this district, I'm incredibly
proud to be a part of this
community that values diversity
and support guys diversity
and supports organizations such
as ours in fostering inclusion,
education and cultural pride.
This acknowledgment inspires us
to continue building bridges
and uplifting the voices of our
aapi neighbors.
This recognition is especially
meaningful as me is also what
makes fifty-firsts anniversary
spring gala and I would love to
extend an invitation to y'all
here to join us while me as a
partner of alice fong yu as
their afterschool program
provider.
We also want to congratulate
MISS Liana szeto so this
recognition and award for her
commitment and dedication to
bilingual learning and we wish
her a happy retirement.
Thank you again everybody.
And let's keep celebrating
and shape a better future for
all of us.
>> thank you.
>> I'll be brief.
My name's lily.
I'm the director of the center
chinese cultural district.
Thank you.
Supervisor and engardio for
recognizing us this month.
I think it's very important to
uplift the api culture.
I also want to thank our board.
Several of our board members
are here today as well as our
sunset community, our staff
and why me as our lead agency
of fiscal sponsor.
I also want to thank all of you
for passing our tests just a
couple of weeks ago.
It was a result of hundreds
probably more than hundreds of
hours of work engaging with the
community and really reflects
our collective goals to
stabilize and uplift our sense
of community.
As supervisor claudio had
mentioned, we were founded was
founded by supervisor ma
in 2021 was legislative back
then and it was really we were
created as a direct result of
what's happened what happened
at the time at the federal
government level where some
in a similar space right now we
are still committed to fighting
for our communities to ensure
that our aapi community is not
scapegoated and having the
lessons learned from four years
ago we refuse to go back to it
.
And we look forward to working
with all of you our sunset
community and our wider aapi
community to ensure that all of
us are protected.
>> thank you.
>> congratulations again.
>> all right.
Congratulations to all of
today's special commendation
honorees.
MADAM Clerk colleagues, this
concludes our 230 special
order.
MADAM Clerk, please call items
number 18 and 19 items 18
and 19 comprise the public
hearing to consider objections
to a report of assessment costs
submitted by the director of
public works for inspection
and or abatement of blighted
conditions ordered to be
performed by said director
pursuant to chapter 80 of the
san francisco administrative
code the costs thereof having
been paid for out of a blight
abatement fund scheduled
pursuant to a motion approved
on APRIL 15th 2025 and just a
further for item 19 this is the
resolution to approve the
report submitted by the
director of public works for
the work that was ordered to be
performed.
The costs having been paid for
out of a blight abatement fund.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk
colleagues we have before us a
hearing on the report of
assessment costs for blighted
properties.
>> we will open this hearing
and first hear from the
department of public works
and I believe we have now simon
and alicia witt presenting.
>> good afternoon, members of
the board.
My name is alicia witt
representing san francisco
public works graffiti unit
chapter 80 of the
administrative code the
community preservation
and blight reduction act
requires that property owners
maintain their property in a
safe and blight free condition.
The code requires public works
to inspect graffiti and notify
property owners to make
corrections.
It is the obligation of the
property owner to maintain the
property free of graffiti
and blight.
Public works notifies property
owners by physical posting at
the property regular mail
and certified mail when blight
is posted the notice of
violation provides information
on how to contact the graffiti
unit, how to request a hearing
and how to request an extension
if more time is needed to abate
accompanied by the notices we
include date and time stamped
colored photos to indicate the
extent and location of the
graffiti for every notice of
violation posted the graffiti
unit makes considerable efforts
to research property ownership,
make courtesy calls or send
courtesy emails with photos to
property owners, property
representatives and or property
tenants alerting them of the
new graffiti vandalism on their
property.
And there are quire meant to
clean it up.
Public works records I mean I'm
sorry public works records show
that the majority of property
owners obey graffiti from their
properties on time if not
abated within the allowed time
a fee is incurred in cases
where the property owner
ignores the notices or refuses
to remove the graffiti, the
city will perform the required
corrections and assess the
costs through the tax roll.
Today we request the approval
of the list for assessment of
blight blighted properties
since there is an outstanding
balance on these properties
public works is requesting that
these assessments be added to
the property tax bill through
this board hearing the
outstanding fees owed are to
recoup abatement and recovery
cost incurred to the city's
general fund.
Thank you so much.
I don't see anything from my
colleagues so what we're going
to do now is go ahead and open
this up for public comment.
So if we have members of the
public who would like to speak
,please line up to the right
of the podium where is the
line?
>> is there one line that's
that's the line back there.
>> I hit the right side of the
podium.
I'm confused back there.
>> correct.
Wait and everybody will have
two minutes to speak for public
comment and you are the first
speaker, sir, if you approach
the microphone.
>> good afternoon.
>> contrary to what they say
they don't always mail you.
I know I've been going through
this probably for a long time.
I've got stacks of them
and usually you get a notice
you have 30 days to abate it.
You take pictures after you
beat it, you send it into the
dpw unit a few times they came
not even 30 days tried to send
me to a hearing and I was able
to reach someone down there
and they agreed with me
and they stopped it this time I
never got anything by mail
can't find any evidence that it
was posted.
All I got was the hearing.
Now I've obviously been trying
to keep up with this.
I maintain my property so I
don't think it's fair that I'm
being assessed a fee when it's
obvious that I'm trying to keep
up this.
Not to mention I did abate it.
The data was abated was APRIL
30th just because I saw it.
The city never came out
and painted anything.
>> I did it myself like always
.
Thank you.
We will hear public comment
from everyone and then everyone
will have an opportunity to
have a conversation with dpw
outside of the chamber to see
if we can come to a resolution.
>> thank you.
>> next speaker please.
>> hi, my name is justino hor
what?
I got a notice about a blight
citation for 2201 market street
citation number 2898689
in voice 412633 I'm not
responsible for 2201 market
street.
I have nothing to do with that
property.
This is a mistake in my name
needs to be removed from the
citation.
I have asked the department of
public works to correct this
issue but even though they
assured me that it was fixed
last time I spoke with them
they failed to fix it.
>> the property owner of 2201
market street is chris foley of
ground matrix.
I brought documentation to show
that chris foley is the owner
of 22 on one market street
including the first and last
pages of the deed of trust an
article talking about the
permit and plans to build a
gigantic eight story apartment
complex on that site and public
notice hearings please remove
my name from citation 2898689
I'm not responsible for this
property have nothing to do
with this property no idea why
my name is associated with this
property please remove me
justino ha what from this
citation thank you joe leave
the documentation anywhere
again to everybody you have
opportunity to have a
conversation with dpw outside
of the chamber after public
comment.
so right now we're just taking
public comment.
Next speaker please.
>> all hello.
>> hi, my name's elation
daniels and I'm founder of
fusion rolls llc.
We're a tech manufacturing
company where we offer globally
inspired healthy appetizers
and meals designed for
convenience without compromise
.
I'm here because I believe
in creating an ecosystem that
brings ownership, innovation
and food access to underserved
communities.
And so our mission is to fight
food insecurity through cutting
edge.
>> are you speaking on a
blighted property because we're
in a hearing right now it is
this public comment is just
specific to this hearing right
now.
>> okay.
>> we will have an opportunity
for public comment later on
in a meeting.
Okay.
No problem.
Thank you.
>> and again we're taking
public comment only on the
blight it properties hearing
next speaker please.
>> good afternoon.
I own the property 36,006 18th
street.
>> sir, can you speak directly
into that microphone?
>> we can hear you best.
So good afternoon.
I'm the owner of the property
at 36 30th 18th street.
Obviously we get a lot of
graffiti and most of the
graffiti is due to the bus stop
directly in front of our
building which is not right.
We clean it every 3 or 4 days.
It's very time consuming
and very costly for us.
You're talking about 80 bucks a
gallon to cover paint and it's
ridiculous to get fined by dpw
when they don't do nothing to
help with the situation.
And it's not fair for us if we
pay so much money and we keep
continuously clean it up.
Obviously we're about the worst
part a lot of foot traffic.
I have pictures.
Shall we clean it up in for a
day?
But if the ongoing battle with
the bus stop and all the people
coming off the bus and tend to
be some bad element and they
always graffiti the brick
building and it's very
difficult to clean the brick.
So we have to paint over it
every time.
So to me to get fined I think
it's ridiculous and I've always
cleaned it and then they I live
and take pictures when they put
another notice but it's always
different graffiti they grew I
graffiti graffiti it I paint
over and then there's another
tag and there's the same one
but it's different tagged every
so often once a month.
So it's a ongoing battle, a big
waste of time for me but I'm
doing my part as a citizen to
help san francisco to keep it
cleaner and better.
But dpw should do their side
maybe with the bus stopped.
>> I don't know who is
responsible but maybe remove
the bus stop and I wouldn't
have this issue anyway.
So I just wanted to thank you
for your time and obviously
talked to dpw and hopefully I
don't have to pay that
ridiculous money that shouldn't
be towards the landlord.
>> all right.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> the next speaker.
>> hi there.
Is this for us to contest or
just to make public comment?
You can make public comment
and everybody will have an
opportunity to speak with a
representative from the
department of public works
after public comment outside of
the chamber.
>> okay.
I'm a property manager for a
property owner.
>> I came here because we
abated the graffiti on the
building that was referenced.
It was at 228 5 in 2 287
mission street.
The citation was to 926117.
It was addressed in time.
We sent an email to the
graffiti unit asking for a
confirmation of receipt that we
had abated it with pictures.
>> we never received a reply
that they had received the
email with the pictures of
showing the abatement and then
we received this follow up
notice saying that we needed to
come here for public comment
and pay the fee.
>> that's all.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker I came here
today expecting to protest the
fine and the posting in this
case I've never received the
the violation in the mail.
>> I didn't know where there
was a violation.
i abate dozens of these
graffiti violations every year
many times I'll send the email
with the pictures I'll still
get the fine in the mail.
I'll respond back to dpw
graffiti unit saying you
improperly find me.
I have proof I sent you the
pictures.
They won't respond to my email
so there's peers or some
disorganization at dpw and if I
would have known there was a
violation I would have abated
it in this case when I saw this
posted I went and painted the
building promptly took down the
posting I'm here today to try
to protest it so I was hoping
there would be a formal process
for contesting these these
these fees so so appreciate it.
>> thanks.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hi, my name is rob
veras on properties 177
information street so I'm here
to make a comment.
So the problem here is this
there's a skate park on two
boats on mission.
There's no young kids there.
There's a bunch of adults that
had nothing should do in their
life and every day every night
they come in store graffiti
in your building every single
morning I have to come in and
clean up this.
I get tired of it and it
doesn't make sense.
I just like skate park days for
kids or for grown adults that
come in destroy the city every
single day.
That's all I got to tell you
guys.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
next speaker hello, my name is
marcella and I'm here speaking
in regards to the property at
2170 mission street.
So specifically we the graffiti
that's kind of being referenced
and fined for originally
occurred a year before my
citation and then when the
citation was put in place it
was literally in DECEMBER
and DECEMBER we're trying to
like as a business operate deal
with guests.
>> you know, we're barely able
to manage like the amount of
things we have to deal with on
a different day.
>> I'm also too like with the
graffiti abatement it's only
for the assistance up to eight
feet this specific graffiti is
I think about 25 feet high.
>> it's pretty high higher than
anybody that could reach on a
normal ladder and on the
rooftop the way the roof is
it's about six feet high
and overhangs directly onto the
cement.
>> it's extremely unsafe
and you know, one thing I was
trying to look for is like
resources try to find
assistance with this and I
think a lot of business owners
in the mission and other parts
of the city, you know, it's a
huge problem because to be able
to paint that you either have
to hire a company or rent
equipment and that's so much
money on already like strained
business operations and what
our costs are and so as far as
actually like correcting it
we're really good about I mean
I have dozens of pictures we're
very, very good about doing
that.
but that specific instance it's
the middle of the holidays.
>> it's raining, it's so unsafe
.
>> so you know, it's there's
not just like noncompliance.
>> right?
There's other things at play.
So thank you, ma'am.
MAY I ask you to repeat the
address?
Thank you.
Next speaker hi.
Good afternoon.
>> my name is anton rae.
I'm the executive director of
goodwill of san francisco bay.
This is in reference to
citation number 2947157 and the
address is one two one
wisconsin street.
>> this is a donation center we
are the tenant.
We actually just learned about
this via an email this morning
and so I just share this
because I think there's an
opportunity to make sure that
the record keeping
and communication is improved
upon.
We have not heard from our
landlord about this and this
was the first communication
received this morning with an
email that happened to go to
our purchasing department
and made its way to me.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker good morning board
members.
>> my name is melanie.
I'm the owner of the building
at 1035 venice avenue and speak
to a degree in o'farrell's
graffiti has been tank our
building at the lower level
street level we always clean it
up but this graffiti happened
to be on a fourth floor.
>> how the graffiti got up
there they had a claim to a
next door neighbor tommy's
joint restaurant from their
they picked the fourth floor
that we did clean up many times
but this time we have enough so
I request the city the city to
give me a notice on the APRIL
3rd 2 or 2 for we reply what
back and what email that we
were up in your form submitted
to us that were up in four city
to erase the graffiti up at
this time we have no idea is
not part of the discourse or
core commercial corridor and if
venice if fairness is not a
commercial code I have no idea
where you can get one.
Venice evros highway one on one
many restaurants, hospitals,
car dealers in my building is a
senior care facility as I
consider this is a commercial
corridor we found out this only
yesterday so I'm asking what is
happening with dpw.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hi, good
afternoon.
My name is brian goldstein.
I'm the senior manager of
facilities for the san
francisco ballet.
This is in reference to our
property our warehouse property
at 2400 cesar chavez which is
in supervisor walton's district
district ten citation number
2898071 our property is located
directly across the street from
department of public works
property and within the past 18
months we have received over 12
notice of violations.
This to us feels a little bit
pointed and we are requesting
assistance both in our ability
to abate this graffiti which is
costing us the san francisco
ballet a tremendous amount of
cost hardship and as a, you
know, arts nonprofit in this
current economy that is
challenging for us to to deal
with and we also would love to
see some more action on the
part of how do we actually
resolve the challenge that is
creating this which is graffiti
.
Cesar chavez is primarily an
industrial location and I think
it's fairly safe to assume that
we will continue to see
graffiti.
But in our case we are getting
notice of violations before the
paint is even dry on our
building.
So we would love any assistance
from the board of supervisors
that we can get to help us
resolve this problem.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker hello.
>> board of supervisors.
My name is the younger me
and my situation number two
story 876037 my address is 1219
harrison street but in your
documents it's 1221 commercial
quarter downstairs every time
something happened to this
building I get notice and I
have to deal with this and now
I got a letter that it will be
on my property tax but it's
already paid by management
company and I would like to be
removed from your list.
>> this is number one.
Number two what's happened
in our area it's absolutely
disrespectful to buildings
and to people who live there.
>> it's dangerous and scary
sometimes I need to run out
and scream and yell because
somebody tried to or crush my
window or write something on
the window on the wall
and that's really unpleasant
when when you have woman
sitting alone and now you know
what we look our daughter
and we ask our clients to knock
on the door because we are
afraid to go out and then this
guy's going out.
>> we trying to see if his able
to sink is fine the round
because dangerous I have really
strange people walking around
sometimes you know I one person
ran with me was homer after me
.
>> it's absolutely
unacceptable.
So please you have power to do
something about this?
>> please.
It's really scary and I
definitely will talk to people
to, you know, remove my name
because it's really wrong.
It's nothing to do with me
and it's already paid off by
association and management
company.
>> I'm done.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker good afternoon
supervisors.
>> my name is tony tamburro I'm
the owner of the property at
214 two boats avenue which is
situated in an historical
district.
I have lived there and I have
been there since 1979
and throughout the years I've
had a number of graffiti on my
building.
>> I have abated them on a
regular basis and now I am now
here because I have paid for
painters, painters and paint
and everything else and I'm now
retired and I can't afford to
rebate.
>> there's a problem that I
think is in what the d p d w
department because I received
the notice that is probably the
thing that you're talking about
at this hearing and I did not
receive the notice and time but
at the same time when I did get
it I called and I didn't call
but I sent in for a request for
a hearing.
I never received any indication
of a hearing date.
I never received anything even
after I called they said don't
worry, it'll come in good time
.
>> I am most importantly the
housing that I have here is on
two sides of vacant driveways
and there was actually a number
of incidents with a unhoused
unhoused people who have
definitely did things.
But I do have one thing I want
to say that is important I've
had two burglaries and they are
two of them were done by
graffiti artists because they
broke in and they left their
spray paint colored cans
and the police confirmed that
and put a report out.
But what I want to say is this
I want to say that I am the
victim of a crime.
>> graffiti is either a
misdemeanor or a felony.
>> thank you, sir, for your
comments.
I want to make like to say want
to thank you for your comments.
You have an opportunity to have
a conversation with the
department next week or please
,I understand that jack, thank
you for your comments.
>> you can feel free to also
email the board as well.
Next speaker please.
>> all right.
>> good afternoon.
My name's pete mahoney.
Can you hear me all right.
I want the property at 200
slash 208 ocean avenue and my
the two store downstairs
and the owner of the business.
He gave me a call and said that
this was posted on the
building.
So only thing I got received
from them and and I went to
look at it and I called public
works.
The man is supposed to be here.
His name is simon over ten
times to try to get an
explanation for what graffiti
he's talking about.
I got photos of the building
and there was never any kind of
graffiti and he wouldn't
respond.
You know, that's he said call
that's the number I call in the
meantime says 2019 I was
in general hospital for the
reason of probably covid but I
was actually dead and put on
life support and I'm not using
that for sympathy.
But I wanted to tell you from
2019 to this date I've been
either in a nursing home or a
hospital or care at home and I
have bought this bright bag.
I don't think you want to look
at it.
What is the proof of the places
that I've been for the last six
years or so and and if I get a
call for any kind of graffiti
on my property I have a friend
that would go out and take care
of it.
The only thing was this posted
in with charlie showed up.
He said you had a notice for
something on the building
and and that was it.
That was it.
And I don't know why that would
put a number to call when the
person named simon does not
respond to any of the phone
calls at all and that doesn't
make sense if you call into
question why a notice was put
on you need to have an answer
from him because he's the one
who placed the I don't know
what else to tell you.
>> there's been graffiti
graffiti before but thank you
sir for your comments and I did
thank you very I'm sorry.
Thank you guys.
Come on.
Come on, guys.
You got it?
Yeah.
No, thank you.
Thank you.
I'll be honest this was just me
too.
>> my apologies.
I just want to say in the
twitter thank you so much.
>> next speaker please.
Is that two minutes?
Okay.
Thank you very much everyone
and certainly who's counting
you?
>> can you hear me?
I am ready, yes.
Okay.
My name is robert holland.
My business address is 1000 to
visit door and 1008 to visit
darryl.
I got a notice of citation at
1696.
i do not own 1696 golden gate
said citation numbers 2870641
okay I have removed a lot of
graffiti imports bricks I know
what it takes for a property
owner to do this type of stuff
because bricks is not easy to
remove.
I do have graffiti acid all
over my glass windows.
Okay since taco but over
and over and over again I
notice you have to speak for me
today that the gentleman that
works too hard and pay people
to erase all the posts, all the
glass all the next day I swear
to you again I'm having the
same problem.
But to make a long story short
I call this city hall the other
day and I was told to bring
this information here because
this is the wrong address.
Okay.
Except been very simple if a
man got the wrong address, the
lady looked it up.
She said we're going to remove
your name from this address
1696 golden gate.
My address is 1000 and 1008
visit no and I know the
hardship of small business
owners that have to go through
this and I hope the city can do
something about it.
>> thank you.
And then I discovered after
they seem like to me they could
have delivered a phone because
the lady did find out
information.
>> but I find myself here
and going outside to thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Hi my name is patty I call is
from the california park
center.
The location is 1475 polk
street and the citation number
is 27202 11.
>> we have social media
graffiti ripping every single
time we received a notice we
remove it and then I send the
email to the graffiti
department and then notified
them I take the picture since
the property is of wine decor
non californian pope is a piece
corner.
After we remove it the graffiti
again and then after we remove
we doing so many time we just
can just like we have nothing
to do just deal with the
confetti in the people put the
garbage in the corner they do
dumping everything.
>> we just clean everything
and besides we pay the property
tax.
We pay 58,000 on property tax.
On the top of that we pay
13,000 for the neighborhood
cleaning.
>> so I don't know why we get
this notice I did not not get
this notice every single time I
got the notice I always respond
right away and this is it's
ridiculous.
We just keep painting, painting
and painting remove the
graffiti.
And the thing is even after we
remove the coffee because they
put the chemical so it just hot
completely remove you still see
something and we paint
colloquium and be painted again
someone got to do something
regarding vat thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker I'm sorry.
>> hello my name is lori.
I represent genesee llc so we
got a citation numbers 2851374
are on the time.
usually we get more citation
for 12 citation for a year.
That means every month here
citation.
So due to the location and we
always paying and pay our labor
to the people and do the good
jobs but one time then they
send us citation to us then we
request more time due to the
ring seasons but the city
doesn't give it any chance.
Finally they still send out a
citation that we have to pay
for but we are really tired for
the coffee.
The people who put diana
graffiti.
>> the city doesn't controlled
it and we pay property tax
and everything so I hope the
city do more.
You know the people who put
in coffee, tea and art do more
things for us and then thank
you for your comments.
Next speaker thank you.
Chair one the board supervisor
my name is larry kemp.
I come here to speak for
chinese consul benevolent
association and many of the
merchants and association
and in chinatown as you know to
start this record gets a lot of
graffiti and it's not this one
time maybe two times a week
that we get it and we abate it
and then it comes back again
in particular for four quba
chinese six we have one that
was on the roof so our property
manager went up there and took
a look.
There's nothing on the roof.
It was basically just a roof.
But in looking at I guess the
complaint it was on the side of
the wall.
>> if you're if you're a senior
or you're I guess a worker out
there, you're not going to lean
over to the side.
So it wasn't duly noted that it
was on the side of the wall,
not on the roof in particular.
Also we want to ask that when
you do send out this notice of
violation that you also include
included in chinese because
many of those shop owners
and associates or monolingual
speak chinese and they say hey,
look at is there are graffiti
to look outside of front of the
building we did too.
We said where is it?
Well, it's up on the roof.
You have to go across the
street to take a look at on the
side a wall.
And so again I say that you do
it in chinese and also I guess
to resolve this issues about
this graffiti throughout the
city that you impose a tax on
these spray spray can can't you
guys do it impose a tax on it
so then you can pay for the
lights that in our city.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker that afternoon my
name is terron patel.
This is regarding 825 polk
street.
We have owned that property
since 1973 in the last 20 years
we have spent well over
$120,000 to clear graffiti.
>> my question to you is where
does it end?
It's this is your time to
provide public comment.
Well, I mean I don't know what
to do anymore since the
pandemic started we have lost
hundreds of thousands of
dollars and then we get these
notices from the city saying
the graffiti is not cleaned up
.
It's not that we don't want to
now in order to paint the area
that graffiti it would cost
over $20,000 and I don't have
the pocket for that anymore so
that's all I had to say.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hi, my name is
john innes.
We own my wife and I own 950
howard about 12 years ago we
bought the building and we
housed a local architecture
firm and we design housing,
affordable housing and in
moderate income housing and all
kinds of housing and I just
wanted to say that I wanted to
commend public works and I will
since they're outside I think
they do a great job.
I think they're fairly
communicative.
I think if you want to own a
building in san francisco
and take the risk of buying it,
you should clean up the
graffiti and I really don't
have a problem with the $360
fine that I got.
It's on the second floor.
>> it was hard to get to but
what I wanted to say is you
have all these owners who have
taken risk to buy buildings
and operate businesses and it
seems a little bit disingenuous
to to get these fines and paint
over this graffiti when I walk
out my door and the 50 or so
employees we have coming
and going early in the morning
and late at night walk over
needles, walk over the drug
users walk over faces the
problem I can't even bring my
parents to this building.
I'd be embarrassed too.
so I appreciate I'm happy to
pay the fines.
I'm happy to clean it but I
just wanted to say there's
something else that needs to be
done with the other problems
that are far outweigh a little
tag on the side of my building
and I don't know if this is the
body that's can help do that
but I think a little bit more
money should go into cleaning
the streets, cleaning up the
camps, making it livable,
making employees who want to
commute from marin county
and the east bay to san
francisco to come to this
office and step over the kind
of inhumanity that exists there
is unfair and it's not sincere
what's happening right here.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
Is this for the regular this is
for the blighted properties
hearing your call for the
regular committee will later
this afternoon we'll have
general public comment.
>> hello I'm a concerned
citizen and I'll just suggest
that you guys instead of making
it like punishing people you
know I think you should appeal
to both sides the property
owners and also people who have
the urge to express their self
in that way, give them a
community and services so that
they can express their self
without fear or harsh
punishments of poverty or
vandalism when people come back
and when people come back to
mark their territory.
I mean like I learned from
learning graffiti history in in
new york, you know people come
back to tag their place because
there's a sense of pride.
I mean maybe if you gave them a
place to represent their sense
of pride it won't be on
people's properties.
Thank you.
Are there any other members of
the public who would like to
address the board regarding
their blighted property?
>> all right.
Or a report of an assessment
cost to their property?
>> okay, MR. PRESIDENT, thank
you.
>> say no more public comment
for this particular hearing.
Public comment is now closed
and I do just want to thank
everyone who came in to speak
and I know I want to let the
public know that we do have
representatives of the
department outside the chamber
so that you can have a
conversation to talk about your
particular situation and just
want to thank you for coming
down and the department really
does try to work with community
so I hope we do come to
resolutions and I see
supervisor sutter thank you
PRESIDENT Are there any members
of dpw still in the room?
I'd like to ask some questions
if so through the PRESIDENT To
supervisor sartor I know that
the three individual is are
in the hallway speaking to
residents at the moment.
>> can we can we get someone
in here MADAM Clerk we
certainly will thank.
>> happy to do it now or to
return to whatever your
preference.
PRESIDENT I believe hopefully
somebody will be walking
in that door within the next
20s and if not that we can call
for recess but that I hope we
don't get to that point
welcome back.
Supervisor souder had a couple
of questions.
Thank you.
PRESIDENT Hi.
I know you're busy out there.
>> a few questions that have
been raised.
>> you know, first just to a
request and a suggestion in the
future when you provide this
list, if we can see the
district number on there, we
spent a lot of time looking at
all these addresses to see what
fell into our district and I'm
sure everyone did the same.
>> the is it is it accurate
that there's no difference
in the fee there's no
difference in the fine for a
graffiti whether it's on the
first floor, whether it's on
the roof, whether it's on the
third floor.
Is that accurate?
>> yes, that's accurate.
So once a 30 day notice of
violation is posted on the
property the property owner has
30 days to abate after the 30
days if the same graffiti still
remains on the property, it's
still the $362 fee regardless
of the location of the graffiti
as long as it's the same
graffiti.
>> thank you.
Not for today but hopefully
something maybe this body
and your office will look at.
I think it's reasonable to
treat it different if it's
something that's on the ground
floor you know, very prominent
on a on a front door versus
something that is small and on
the roof and realizing that for
the property owners it's quite
different to take care of
something maybe yourself on the
on the front door again versus
something that's up on the roof
and we certainly heard from a
number of business owners that
that was the case with their
with their graffiti.
>> I guess my biggest question
is as we're seeing here kind of
the scurry of everyone talking
to you, did you have a workshop
before this?
Did you have an opportunity for
people to ask you questions
and engage or is this the first
time that that form is being
offered so this list was
completed at the end of MARCH
so property owners have been
contacting us whether it's by
email or by phone.
A lot of the property owners do
have our email address phone
number.
We are constantly in contact
with them.
We give them courtesy emails
just so we can do some sort of
outreach and they would know
who to contact.
>> so once again the list has
been completed in MARCH
and from MARCH until now we
have been receiving calls
and emails from property owners
that either wants to just say
pay the fee or we're looking
deeper into it to see if it
needs to be waived.
We want to make sure that you
know, there isn't a mistake on
our end because we want to make
sure that we are fair to the
property owners of san
francisco.
So we do dig deeper into each
photo to make sure it is the
same graffiti that still
remains the graffiti is from
2024.
So in the hallway right now
we're getting you know, people
that think it's for 2025
graffiti.
>> so we're just trying to
explain to them that this
graffiti is from 2024
and things that have been
missed and was outside of the
30 day notice of violation that
was given.
>> thank you.
And I want to appreciate that
there's a lot of well there's a
lot of work that you do on this
and there's a lot of back
and forth that happens.
Right.
I understand there's inevitably
going to be missed addresses or
communication.
That's not necessarily my
concern.
My concern is is why we're
having that process held here.
It seems like a very poor use
of everyone's time as you're
seeing once you get together
in the hallway like you're
having that communication
and it's not you know, the days
in between emails or calls it
seems like there should be some
sort of workshop or or option
for that before it gets to this
point.
I think that's probably a
better use of everyone's time
and I'd like to see that in the
future.
Frankly at this point I don't
know what we're supposed to do
given that you've got, you
know, dozens of people outside
right now that are working on
this.
so maybe I'll come back with
some ideas on that.
>> thanks.
Okay.
Thank you.
Supervisor souder.
And I just want to say I think
that we would all rather not
have this take place here
in the board chamber, but by
law we have to hear these.
>> so that's that's why we're
here.
But yes, this is something that
probably could be worked on for
the future.
>> supervisor fielder, thank
you so much.
>> my question is about the
communication because a couple
of a handful of folks talked
about how they have reached out
to dpw to show pictures that
they have abated their issue
that they've been cited for
and that a lot of them have not
heard back.
Can you walk us through the the
kind of process for you know,
someone gets a citation, what
is their expectation around
them communicating that they've
abated this what is their
recourse for contesting it?
>> so once a call comes in 2311
from a member of the public
saying that there's graffiti on
the property, the inspectors
have a total of three days to
go to the property to post a
notice of violation.
>> that notice of violation
gives the property owner 30
days to abate the graffiti.
After 30 days a blight notice
can be posted on the pop on the
property.
>> the blight notice is what
carries that $362 fee.
Now once the notice of
violation is posted there is an
administrative staff that will
reach out to the property owner
because typically we MAY
already have their email
address or phone number.
They reach out same day once
they contact them just to let
them know that there is
graffiti on the property.
>> property owner say no
problem thank you for calling
me I will get this abated.
The property owners that do not
abate it within the 30 days
after the courtesy call that we
do or a courtesy email those
are the property owners that
are getting the blight notice
posted after the 30 days so
after the blight notice is
posted on the property that's
when they receive the fee.
>> even at that time there's a
certified letter that is mailed
to the property owner once the
blight notice is posted on the
property and at that time they
do have the opportunity to pay
the fee before it gets to this
point.
>> this point is when property
owners have not paid the fee
for the blight from last year
and these are the properties
that are outstanding and that's
why we're here.
Understood.
There is some sort of it seems
like there is some sort of
breakdown in communication.
I don't know if it's because
maybe dpw doesn't happen to
have the accurate phone number
outside of dpw control accurate
email I'm not sure but there's
a clear breakdown
in communication where it seems
that property owners are
addressing the city or the
issue but for some reason are
not hearing back and I'm trying
to understand what the
breakdown is.
>> if you all have any insight,
if you have any further.
>> hello everyone.
I mean just to her point, you
know, we do put a physical
piece of paper on the property
and like the same day we send a
letter out email.
So there's like a lot of ways
to try to communicate to the
property owner once the
property owners it's it's it's
up to them if they're going to
comply with the abatement or
the fee and just like how we
were outside it could just be
something as simple as someone
saying oh I never got the
paper, I never got the email.
So we're taking their word for
it that that's the case.
But we have proof of stamp
photos from each inspector
going to the property on the 30
days on 45th day or whatever
day it was showing that the
graffiti remained.
>> so there is times where the
property owners, you know,
aren't being very truthful
which it happens but you know
sometimes we try to take
everyone's word for it and try
to, you know, work with them
and whatever, you know,
hardship they're going through
.
We do these hardship hearings
or do offer them these you
know, we do have I don't know
if you guys are aware the opt
in programs with now there
in the corridor is to help out
with public works helping them
out with abatements but but
like I said you know we i
believe we go through many
steps to try and get to the
property owners so with that
being said, thank you and sorry
last question so will some of
the property owners who have
proved that they have abated
these issues, will they have
their fees dismissed today?
>> correct.
They will have their fees
dismissed.
I am making a note of the
property owner's email address.
So for those notice of
violations or in our graffiti
management system that we have
I'm making it a point to get
everyone's email address that's
in the hall right now to make
sure going forward at least we
have this information here
we've had some issues where
property owners have bought a
property and the person or the
property owner prior did not
just say pay the fee so now
they're receiving the
information they are having
some issues with just say the
assessor's recorder's office.
It's pulling information for
property that's not theirs.
So we are facing different
things in the hallway right now
and those properties are being
waived so we're getting more
information and it's great
feedback that we're getting
from them so we know how to
proceed going forward with
this.
Okay.
>> thank you so much.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder supervisor
chin thank you, PRESIDENT Hi.
>> I know that on one one of
the public comment also
mentioned are about translation
and so I actually on MAY 32nd
of the merchants on mission
street their dashti merchant
they're not happy owner so they
got a four page off notice so
that's all tape when they you
know start their business on a
day they were they got scared
because they didn't know like
what violation they actually
violated so I wonder what is
currently the but the notice
how many language do you send
out or just one I believe it is
just one language.
That's something we would have
to contact our communications
team to see if they would have
someone that can translate
those notices into different
languages to make sure going
forward everyone understands
what the notice is and what to
do.
>> yeah this is especially
important I speak for my own
district district 11 where
spanish and chinese is
definitely very important
and also I know that
in chinatown I larry commission
I just mentioned in chinatown
to a lot of a small publicly
home owner it's and plus
merchants are all pretty
monolingual so having that that
will really help with the small
business and also the clear
communication because I did
look into some of the document
that I receive from the
merchant.
>> it's one it's it's
addressing it too directly to
the property owner.
The other notice has no it just
it has no address to anybody.
So it was definitely very
legitimate for the merchant to
also concern like what
violation did they violate so
and I'll office call
and definitely got really quick
response from your office I
want to thank that but also
looking into how can we make
sure that translation is
available.
>> okay thank you.
Thank you.
Supervisor chin stuber I just
outer thank you PRESIDENT So
with the conversations
happening in the hallway right
now, is it your intent to make
amendments to this list of
properties?
I'm just trying to understand
how we're supposed to consider
and vote on this today.
>> so for the property owners
that are in the hallway that
have showed up to day, they're
giving us the reason why they
feel they shouldn't receive the
fee.
So we're listening to everyone
that's in the hallway and we
are waiving the fees
accordingly to what they are
presenting to us.
>> so we hear that information
today or I believe we're
supposed to come back super
excited we will typically at
this works a lot of this gets
resolved when we allow public
works to be out working with
all of the folks who have
concerns in the hallway
and then they come back to us
so we closed the hearing.
Then we allowed dpw to work
with the residents and then
they come back with an updated
list typically supervisor chan
did you still have just that we
should move on so that the
public waiting outside is not
going to get angrier at our
department of public works
and they get to get back to
work and resolve this.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT.
Thanks to rosa chen and thank
you so much to the department.
>> we are going to close this
hearing right now and we will
come back to item 19 later
in the meeting the department
will come back and let us know
what has been amended and how
to move forward pretty soon
with that, MADAM Clerk, can you
please go to our next special
order items 20 through 27?
>> thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
I'll begin with items 20
through 23.
These are the items that
pertain to the public hearing
of persons interested in the
determination of exemption from
environmental review under the
california environmental
quality act issued as a
categorical exemption by the
planning department on APRIL
5th, 2024 for the proposed
project at 1310 junipero serra
boulevard which proposes the
demolition of nine maintenance
and facility structures
and construction of a 25 foot
tall one story maintenance
building approximately 20,000
gross square feet in size.
Item 21 is the motion that
affirms the planning
department's exemption
determination.
Item 22 is the motion that
conditionally reverses the
department's exemption
determination subject to the
adoption of written findings.
Item 23 is the motion to
prepare the findings for items
24 through 27 public hearing of
persons interested in the
approval of a conditional use
authorization for the project
at 1310 junipero serra
boulevard issued by the
planning commission by its
motion dated FEBRUARY 13th 2025
to allow the construction of a
19,100 gross square foot one
storey accessory maintenance
and facility building for an
existing open area recreation
area use item 25 is the motion
to approve the commission's
decision to approve the
conditional use authorization.
>> item 26 is the motion to
disapprove the department's
decision to approve a
conditional use authorization
and pursuant to charter section
4.105 and planning code section
308.1 sub d approval of item 26
which would be which would
disapprove the decision of the
planning commission and perhaps
with conditions would be not
less than two thirds vote of
the board or eight votes of the
board and item 27 is the motion
to direct the preparation of
findings in support of the
board's disapproval of the
conditional use authorization.
>> thank you so much, MADAM
Clerk supervisor miller thank
you so much.
PRESIDENT Walton colleagues
thank you so much for your
patience with these items.
My office is still working with
both parties.
We are very close to a
resolution but not quite there
yet.
So with the consent of both the
appellant and the project
sponsor I would like to make a
motion to continue this for one
more week.
>> thank you.
do we have a second on a motion
seconded by supervisor chen
and of course before we go to
vote on that motion we will
open it up for public comment
for anyone who wants to speak
directly and specifically only
about the motion to continue
this item to next week.
>> thank you supervisors thank
you.
Supervisor miller for your help
in this I am the appellant for
the sica and I am in in
agreement with can you grab
that microphone closer so we
can hear you best?
I am the appellant for the
sequel appeal and I am
in agreement with continuing
this for one week.
Thank you for your patience
with us but we are very close
to being on the same page.
>> thank you.
>> >> good afternoon.
My name is joe duncan.
I am a parent of a first grader
at saint thomas moore and I
support the continuance what I
would like to leave with
everyone here is that there is
164 acres to build this
facility and putting it up
against a school and a
preschool is immoral
and despicable.
But hopefully we can find a
reasonable agreement with the
sponsor.
>> thank you.
>> good afternoon.
Members of the board of
supervisors.
My name is alejandro leonard
and I'm the mother of two
children at saint thomas moore
school.
>> I am in support of the
continuance because this is an
issue that weighs heavily on my
heart.
As a mother I want what's best
for my children and they're not
only my world but their safety
is my priority.
So a 20,000 square foot
maintenance facility with
vehicles, fumes, lithium
batteries right next to where
they play and spend most of
their day outside.
It's not desirable.
It's not necessary.
It's scary for many of us.
So I ask you guys today, today
and in the future to prioritize
our children, children and your
city children whose health
and safety depend on you to
stand up for them and children
who are the future of this
city?
Pick them and support them
and show them that they matter
more than a building.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker welcome.
>> hi, good afternoon.
My name is maria bilodeau
and thank you for your time
today.
I am also a parent of two small
children in kindergarten and in
third grade at saint thomas
more.
>> we appreciate the thought
and effort into our all of our
concerns.
>> currently the property has
more than ample space that can
accommodate the maintenance
building and we are asking for
your support to keep our
children safe.
>> many of our children
currently suffer including my
children from allergies
and asthma and we are asking
for just to consider their
health and the current health
and our future students at
saint thomas more.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon members of
the board of supervisors.
I speak in support of the
continuance.
My name is david greenbaum.
I'm a proud native san
franciscan and have always
loved my city.
For more than 25 years I've
been an educator for much of
that time in san francisco
first at our lady of visitation
and then more than a decade
with san francisco unified
school district at bret hart
drew tenderloin community
school malcolm x rooftop
sunnyside jefferson bryant cub
elementary.
Cesar chavez.
Spring valley.
Frank mcalpin.
Francis scott key and for four
years at visitation valley
middle school.
Today I am the principal of st
thomas more school.
This school has been a part of
san francisco for 70 years.
We have nearly 300 students
ages 2 to 3 from preschool to
the eighth grade.
We are a diverse, multiethnic,
multiracial working class
community.
The same community that I
myself am a part of.
While many schools have
downsized or even shut down
in recent years, we are a
growing and thriving community
and we'd like to see that
continue.
>> that is why I am here today.
For more than two years we have
been working in good faith with
the san francisco golf club.
>> the proposed industrial
building is right next to our
preschool fence line about ten
yards away.
The project was deemed exempt
from sequa even though it
included plans for a gas tank,
a chemical shed, lithium I am
charging stations and a
chemical wash station right
next to our preschool outdoor
play space.
>> outrage from parents
and local community adjusted
some of these plans.
>> but we still do not
understand why the project was
deemed exempt from sequa when
it is a stone's throw away from
our school.
>> it is my job to serve
and protect every single child
staff and community member at
my school.
>> if the center school golf
club desires to use the
adjacent lot to saint thomas
more school for a construction
project then they should join
us in voluntarily demanding a
sequel review.
>> even if it takes years for
the good of our entire
community, the safety, health
and well-being of our children
have to come first.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome.
Next speaker.
My name is david joy, resident
of district four.
Thank you.
Supervisor melgar for
forwarding this suggestion of a
continuance.
I am the appellant for the
c-usa.
I'm also a contractor and a
foster parent.
Founding director family house.
I know something about kids
health and I am intimately
involved in the discussions
with the sponsors about
strengthening the walls against
explosions.
I am in favor of the
continuance and I thank you for
your time.
>> thank you for your comments
.
Right.
Any other member of the public
would like to address the board
on either the zika or the c u
items 20 through 27.
>> all right, MR. PRESIDENT,
thank you.
In other speakers public
comment is now closed.
We have a motion to continue
items 20 through 27 to our
tuesday MAY 20th 25.
Board of supervisors meeting
made by supervisor melgar
and seconded by supervisor chan
on a motion.
>> MADAM Clerk.
Supervisor fielder I fielder I
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor sadr I sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton I walton I
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
and supervisor engardio
in gaudio I there are ten I's
thank you motion to continue
this item to next week's board
meeting is past.
>> MADAM Clerk we are back at
roll call for introductions.
>> we'll pick up with
supervisor sartor submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor cheryl submit.
>> thank you supervisor walton
.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I'm
introducing a hearing request
to get to the bottom of the
recent allegations about the
san francisco parks alliance
having misspent restricted
funds from a wide range of
local parks and open space
organizations according to
recent new reports.
It appears that these funds MAY
have been siphoned off to pay
for parks alliance's operating
costs in violation of their
fiduciary and contractual
duties to these organizations.
The parks alliance, whose long
term excessive executive
director recently left has been
slow in being forthright with
these organizations city
agencies and the public.
>> so it is time to use this
board's powers of inquiry
including if necessary our
subpoena powers.
It has been widely reported
that the parks alliance, which
serves as a fiscal sponsor for
some 80 neighborhood based
friends of local park
organizations including a
number in district ten has been
unable to timely reimburse
these organizations for funds
that they hold on their behalf.
>> I am also deeply troubled by
the fact that there are city
departments including the port
of san francisco and our rec
and parks department that MAY
be negatively impact.
I need to remind all of us that
our concerns regarding the
parks alliance go back at least
five years after they were
implicated in a scandal for
taking almost $1 million from
recology in exchange for
favorable garbage rates.
Subsequently this board held
hearings about the parks
alliance.
In 2021 I raised specific
concerns regarding the port's
request to enter into an mou
and accept and expand grants.
Ultimately in 2022 the board
approved this request to
receive 3.25 million in grant
funds for crane cove park for
the parks alliance.
After we insisted on
significant changes
and safeguards thus far it is
my understanding that the port
has received $975,000 of these
funds and it is unclear if the
parks alliance will be able to
provide the balance of the
funds owed.
Also I was shocked to find out
that after our approvals the
port did not end up entering
into the mou that this board
approved in 2023.
This board approved grant
agreement with the parks
alliance for $2 million to
benefit india basin shoreline
park in my district.
It is unclear whether we have
received the benefits provided
for under that agreement
and there are numerous other
agreements rec and park has
with the parks alliance.
We need to know the status of
all of these grants.
Last week parks alliance made
conflicting statements to the
press regarding what has
transpired a parks alliance
board member was quoted as
saying they had not spent the
restricted funds but was then
contradicted by their board
PRESIDENT Who said that they
had.
We need a full financial
accounting from parks alliance
and our city agencies as well
as answers to how the city
intends to recoup funds owed to
us and to many of these
organizations that MAY be
in jeopardy.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor chen submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
>> colleagues with today's
final passage of the recovery
first ordinance I am calling
for a hearing to solicit input
from relative relevant city
agencies for possible revisions
to the 2021 ordinance mandating
annual reports on overdose
prevention policies with long
term recovery from substance
use disorders.
Poised to be enshrined as the
primary goal of san francisco's
drug policy.
I hope to hear from department
heads and drug treatment
professionals on how we might
best update and expand upon
this annual reporting mandate
so that moving forward will
receive departmental recovery
and overdose prevention reports
every year.
Agencies currently required to
report under this law are the
department of public health,
the department of homelessness
and supportive housing.
h soc which is the healthy
streets operations center
through the department of
emergency management and the
human services agency.
Currently these annual reports
generally serve to inform us
about how our city agencies
together with their nonprofit
contractors offer services to
people who use drugs to help
them use drugs more safely
and to help reduce overdoses.
Now obviously overdose
prevention is necessary but not
sufficient for us as a drug
policy strategy.
One thing I think everyone seem
to agree on in the debate
around recovery first was that
drug recovery and drug use for
that matter aren't linear
and that there is no one size
fits all approach.
This hearing on how we best
implement recovery and overdose
prevention policies will
reflect the truth that not
every person who uses drugs
wants to keep using drugs
in perpetuity for those who do.
Yes of course we should
encourage harm reduction
practices to use deadly drugs
more safely.
But for the many san
franciscans struggling with
substance use disorders who
want to be in recovery or who
aspire to live a self-directed
and healthy life free from
illicit drug use as our
recovery first policy reflects
,it only makes sense that we
should hear from city
departments on what roles they
can play to help accomplish
that.
This hearing on recovery
and overdose prevention
policies is an important step
forward in that regard.
I want to thank mayor larry's
team and his department heads
for their openness to
collaborating on this and other
steps to elevate long term
recovery in our drug policy
approach.
Thanks as well to colleagues
PRESIDENT Randleman
in particular is joining me as
a hearing co-sponsor and I
certainly welcome others.
Mostly, however, I want to
thank those in san francisco's
recovery community.
I am continually inspired by
those who have been showing up
and speaking out in increasing
numbers not to criticize or
condemn but to ask for a role
to play in the drug crisis we
face.
I saw it just last night with
dozens of people who showed up
for a community meeting at the
queen hotel in my neighborhood.
The queen will be a first of
its kind recovery oriented
health respite facility for
unhoused adults fighting to get
and to stay clean and sober.
It is moving to see so many
recovery community members
willing to help others who face
challenges similar to those we
have faced to carry the message
that grappling with a drug
addiction need not condemn
anyone to a lifetime of drug
use and to bear witness to the
truth that the promise of
recovery for a better,
healthier life free of illicit
drug use is possible for every
san franciscan who wants it
and the rest I submit.
>> thank you supervisor dorsey
supervisor and gaudio.
submit.
All right, MR. PRESIDENT.
Seeing no names on the roster
that concludes the introduction
of new business.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> let's go to public comment.
At this time the board welcomes
your general public comment.
If you line up on your right
hand side of the chamber you
are able to speak to the APRIL
8th 2025 board meeting minutes
as presented.
Additionally, the mayoral
appearance mayor daniel lurie
his comments in the chamber
today and other general matters
that are not on the agenda but
must be within the board
subject matter jurisdiction
and we are setting the timer
for two minutes.
I'll just state this is not an
opportunity to to speak to any
of the items previously on
today's agenda that had a
public hearing or if the item
had gone to committee.
>> so with me chris will begin
for a change.
>> okay.
Good afternoon board of
supervisors.
>> for the record my name is
chris ward klein.
I also go by sergeant klein of
the united states marine corps.
Last week I spoke a various
commission meetings and over
the last two days hundreds of
my emails were deleted by
several current and former
former city employees.
I know who they are, who these
people are.
All the emails are saved in a
military secured sense or
folder.
So we have the emails but it
was done to obstruct because of
the information that I have
been sharing.
>> so with health and public
safety surveillance it's a
great idea to guide people to
healthy solutions.
However what is happening
in san francisco is several
gave access to universities
and corporations to use their
surveillance systems here
in san francisco and sometimes
they do things that they
shouldn't do and people end up
getting hurt or dying very
serious.
The university was harvard
university but they were not
the only one.
They use rgv spectrum one
system and they have a higher
frequency that they use to try
and discredit people, try to
get people evicted that have
the knowledge of what's going
on.
Again, the emails are saved by
the military the united states
marine corps.
And here's the fbi report that
was submitted today.
It's very unfortunate that a
few people would try and ruin
everyone's reputation in here
because of they want to just
make a little extra money.
It's very unfortunate and I'm
asking everybody here to
convene a justice council
meeting which deals with
surveillance public safety,
public health and also get with
the mayor and have a serious
conversation about who and who
should have access to this
and what's going to happen to
these individuals.
The department of justice will
be coming in very soon.
thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
Welcome.
>> thank you for having me.
My name is jonathan mansour
and I'm honored to serve as
senior director of government
affairs for jcr bay area.
We are the largest collective
voice of bay area jews
representing over 70 synagogues
and organizations including
over a dozen here in san
francisco.
I want to thank PRESIDENT
Mandell man supervisor malcolm
and the whole board for
coauthoring item 33 declaring
MAY as jewish american heritage
month.
This resolution comes at a
crucial time as last year the
jewish community was impacted
by the largest number of
anti-semitic incidents ever
and 42% of bay area jews
reported directly witnessing or
experiencing antisemitism at
2024 ajc rc we believe that one
of the main drivers of this
hate is a fundamental
misunderstanding of jewish
identity and the narrow view
that we are exclusively a
homogeneous religious
minorities and correct.
We are a diverse ethno
religious group that connects
to our identity through
culture, religion, history
and values.
>> here in the bay area, 25
percent of jewish families
include a person of color.
15% of jews identifies lgbtq
and many including myself are
first generation americans.
>> while this resolution is a
good first step to recognize
the diversity of jewish
identity, I hope that will
commit ourselves to doing even
more.
Let's ensure that jewish
holidays are recognized
in civic spaces.
>> let's ensure jewish identity
is included in government d-I
trainings.
Let's ensure that our school
curriculum and activities are
more inclusive of the jewish
experience.
And yes, let's ensure that we
are united communities and not
dividing us based on
geopolitical issues abroad.
I really want to thank you from
the bottom of my heart for your
commitment to supporting the
jewish community and protecting
san francisco as a welcoming
city for all residents.
Thank you for the opportunity.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
>> my name is lillian archer.
I'm a mother of three children,
a small business owner and a
resident of san francisco
deeply concerned about
pedestrians safety.
There was another hit and run
this morning, this time at bay
shore and jerrold near 101
and cesar chavez on ramp.
>> that intersection is a known
danger and has been known for
several years.
>> we've called it out before
and yet here we are again.
>> san francisco's commitment
to vision zero and 2014 has yet
to be reached.
The promise rings hollow when
people are still being killed
in places we already know are
unsafe pedestrian safety is
street safety when a street is
safe for someone walking it's
safer for everyone bikers,
drivers, kids, seniors
and people with disabilities.
We don't need more studies.
We need bold action daylighting
protected intersection
intersections, reduce speeds,
speed cameras, real enforcement
and the sense of urgency equal
to the stakes.
Please act now.
People are being killed and the
time for delays is over.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> welcome.
My name is salah hackett
chandler and I'm coming today
as the representative of the
cultural black hebrew nation to
discuss the proper
classification and the
identification of who the black
ancient hebrew people are.
It has been stated that MR. Eli
MS. Is an african-american
scuse me an african yet an
african-american because he is
from south africa which this is
a dialog that needs to be
discussed that the
african-american people
and their classification is not
properly identified.
It is an exclusive appeal for
all true hebrews to return onto
your real name and give elohim
the praises only.
It is now time for the black
nation to be identified
and classify to their true
identity.
We come in various colors.
Hebrews means various colors
male and female and various
colors.
We are spiritual and ancient
and tribal people.
The reason that our issues are
not identified is because we
don't have the right
classification.
It is now time for america to
do what is decent and in order
for them to do to identify us
as a black nation to discuss
our issues priority reparations
.
Priority reparations.
What is being done in this
country is a disrespect and a
dishonor of what's going on
with captain ibrahim toure ray
.
We stand in allegiance with
ibrahim toure ray.
>> it is time to stop taking
our natural resources and what
identifies with us as a nation.
It is time for us to be put on
this table as the blacks as the
hebrew nation which was stolen
and hijacked from us.
Thank you very much.
>> thank you.
Salah haka chandler for your
comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
>> hello.
Hi board thank you once again
my name's ally shiny daniels
and I'm founder of fusion rolls
where frozen food tech
manufacturing company.
I'm here because I believe
in creating an ecosystem that
brings ownership innovation
and food access to underserved
communities and minority owned
businesses businesses like
minds in san francisco.
Our mission is to fight food
insecurity through cutting edge
food tech like extrusion in 3d
food printing while creating
jobs and teaching
entrepreneurship.
We want to empower people who
feel left out of the system
especially women, minorities
and youths with real
opportunities in food
manufacturing ownership
and tech driven sustainable
city.
We are seeking support to build
this ecosystem with city backed
resources, access to innovation
hubs in alignment with
community based economic
initiatives.
Together we can make san
francisco a leader in exclusive
food innovation and economic
empowerment as a review as you
review real estate in housing
investments in bayview like the
lease at 3801 third street, I
encourage you to include small
local food businesses like ours
and conversations around tenant
partnerships, food access
and community economic
development.
We're also open to supporting
programs like homeless parental
and human services with
catering, nutrition, education
and workforce opportunities.
A fusion of roles is ready to
serve in san francisco not just
with food but with impact.
Thank you for your time.
You can contact me at fusion
rolls llc or gmail.Com.
>> thank you.
Thank you alicia daniels for
your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
Thank you for hearing my
comment today.
My name is kimberly howley.
I am a district eight resident.
I live across the street from
keyser stadium right at the
intersection of where d five,
d, seven and eight all meet
like many in my neighborhood, I
was alarmed to learn that a new
privately owned soccer team has
come to a verbal deal to use
the stadium with almost no
community input.
I'm concerned that the only
community members that were
consulted in those on the
elusive keyser advisory council
were not made aware of the
clause in the deal that would
grant the new team exclusive
access pushing out the
established beloved homegrown
S.F. City football club.
While this deal happened behind
closed doors, I saw S.F. City
special olympians and kids from
one to 92 walking, running
and playing at keyser while the
press mentions that public
access won't be affected name
dropping a notable annual game
or two that can still happen on
the field any good neighbor
knows that the stadium is used
a lot more often and for many
more reasons than the mentioned
exceptions.
As a city we can't rush into
this deal.
Allowing it to go forward would
be like permitting google
shuttles to use muni stops or
kicking out the established
transit lines.
We obviously found a compromise
there.
I'm not saying that there's no
space for a new soccer team at
keyser or any benefit to the
city from adding a new one.
What I am saying is that it
needs to happen in a way that
does not displace the existing
team or the thousands of
residents who depend on this
city jam.
We are elderly neighbors
walking the upper lap to stay
mobile for our grandchildren.
We are families watching our
high school seniors take the
field to graduate.
We are fans cheering for the
oldest community owned soccer
club in the country.
Keys are for the people.
Thank you.
Thank you kimberly halley for
your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
Hello my name is ramona and I'm
a reporter and editor on the
law level student news
publication.
Thank you supervisor melgar for
creating the resolution to
support student journalism at
law and across from cisco
and thank you to supervisors
in garcia fielder ten cheryl
sutton mahmood for sponsoring
this resolution as well I will
be speaking on the reassignment
of the laws journalism advisor
eric gustafson when I joined
the law in my sophomore year I
wasn't sure where to start as a
journalist.
However, my journalism teacher
eric gustafson gave me the
guidance that gave me the
guidance and instruction that I
needed.
I am deeply grateful for the
mentorship and instruction that
he provides me and other
members of the law staff in the
motivation that he's given all
of us.
The goal would not be the
publication that is without MR.
G.
It is so clear that MR. Jacobs
deeply about the publication
enough to spend his own friday
nights waiting for us to finish
editing our magazines.
That commitment to law is an
invaluable quality and inspires
all of us to put our best
effort forward every day.
That's why we were incredibly
shocked and saddened to hear
that MR. G has been reassigned
from his role as a journalism
advisor.
>> MR. G made it clear that as
he worked to reverse the
decision he was doing so to
defend not himself but instead
our best interests as student
journalists and the future of
the law.
It is that attitude that
inspired me today to advocate
for what I know will be best
for a publication.
I believe that reassigning MR.
G and removing him from his
position on the law will
deprive future generations of
all students of the education
expertise and guidance that MR.
G provides in his role as
advisor.
It is not in the best interest
of the quality of work the law
produces or its status as a
respected part of the school
community to make this change.
>> for these reasons I asked
laws administration and sfa to
reconsider the decision to
resign.
MR. G.
I sincerely hope that we can
move forward and work with
s office d in the
administration to find a
solution that does not in move
involve removing the c g is
inviting.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments
ramona.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
Welcome.
>> hello.
My name is thomas harrison
and I'm a reporter and editor
for the law law high school
student publication.
>> like ramona, I would like to
thank supervisor melgar for
creating the resolution to
support student journalism at
lowell and all across san
francisco as well as thank
supervisors and garcia fielder,
chen, cheryl sadr and mahmud
for sponsoring said resolution.
>> as someone who has been
in the law for three years
under erika substance
advisement the protection of
journalism is an issue that I
hold very dear and it means a
lot to me and the rest of our
staff that you've decided to
shed light on it.
Throughout my three years
in the law gustafsson or MR. Ji
as we call him has convened to
show not just expertise but
also an enthusiasm for
journalism that has spread to
every member of our staff
and become the bedrock of our
publication.
He has gone above and beyond
in pushing each and every one
of us to be the best at our
roles that we can be.
And he works hard to ensure
that our reporting is fair,
honest and well-researched.
His insights, support
and dedication have been
invaluable to us and is because
of MR. Ji and his advisement.
>> they have been inspired to
pursue journalism as my major
in college.
i firmly believe that laws
administration's decision to
reassign MR. Ji from his role
as the laws advisor is against
the best interests of the law.
>> if our administration were
to go through with this they'll
be robbing future students of
his expertise and dedication
in my eyes.
His involvement has been part
of our success not just as a
publication but as individual
reporters, photographers,
illustrators and beyond.
I and much of the law staff
sincerely hope the sfa will
reconsider their decision
and retain MR. Ji as our
advisor.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you thomas for your
comments.
>> welcome to the next speaker
.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is iman ansari and I
represent district 11 on the
san francisco youth commission.
Student journalism is
incredibly important as it acts
as a space for youth in the
city to use their voice.
Infringements against student
journalism are unacceptable
and should not be tolerated
in san francisco or anywhere
else.
The incident that occurred at
lowell high school as well as
similar incidents around the
bay area send a negative
message to students.
San francisco should be
striving to give student
journalists a comfortable,
secure place to practice free
speech.
>> the youth commission
strongly believes in the
advancement of student
journalism and we urge the
board of supervisors to take
action by stating their support
and desire to protect
and empower student journalists
.
On MAY 19th the four youth
commission will also discuss
and vote on a resolution
calling for the protection
empowerment and support of
student journalists in san
francisco.
>> we greatly appreciate the
proposed resolution and the
attention to this issue.
We hope this resolution leads
to the further protection of
student journalists in our city
who are facing challenges
against their right to free
speech.
Thank you.
>> thank you, commissioner
and sorry for your comments.
>> welcome.
>> hello supervisors.
My name is hayden.
I'm the former district five
youth commissioner and I
currently live in district one.
I graduated lowell last year
and had the privilege of being
part of lowell's journalism
program for two years.
>> journalism was an invaluable
part of my education.
I never really enjoyed writing
in school until I found the
journalism program because
journalism allowed me to not
just write about abstract
literature and I don't know
books that weren't always my
favorite but it was real.
It was about issues in my
community at our school and it
challenged me to think
critically about these issues
and get out and hear the public
opinion.
And I think it's kind of what
drew me into government as
well.
And I think the reason the
program was so rewarding is
because of our advisor eric
gustafson dedication to the
program.
As previous speakers have
mentioned, he went above
and beyond his role staying
late into the night you know,
giving us food and goodies to
keep us going on in date and he
really is what made the program
successful and a key part of
his advisory ship is that he
really empowers the students.
So when there's attempts to
censor and reassign him from
the program, it's not just an
attack on him but it's an
attack on student voices
and the program as a whole.
I really want to thank
supervisor melgar and the board
as a whole for supporting this
resolution and I urge your I
vote today and support for this
critical program.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments
.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
Welcome supervisor.
Good afternoon.
Thanks for having me here
today.
My name is david lee.
I'm a board member of one of
our homegrown soccer teams, san
francisco city football club.
I'm also a constituent of
district eight and a member of
the S.F. Community that I call
home.
>> I'm not only here today on
behalf of S.F. City fc.
I'm also here to represent
homegrown organizations like
those that we honored earlier
alfaro little football club.
Alice fong you alternative
school and many of the other
organic communities that we
have in san francisco today.
I am here in response to
supervisor mahmud's resolution
with improvements to kezar
stadium.
We are happy to hear about the
growth of this city.
We love this city.
We want it to grow but we want
to make sure that we are doing
it right with the input of the
community.
So fundamentally we take issue
to how quickly the private
agreement for keyser is being
fast tracked.
Since the official announcement
last friday to prevent to
privatize public spaces like
keyser and to give control over
to a private funded for profit
organization and that is how we
displace organizations
and homegrown communities just
like san francisco city
football club or san francisco
nighthawks and the women's
soccer team that plays there.
>> we are already rooted
in community through
partnerships like with
organizations like S.F. Youth
soccer and I think
fundamentally we do not build
public equity by bypassing the
people who built these
institutions.
So for the board I ask that you
uplift long standing
organizations like S.F. City,
like alito and grove and thank
you counsel or ask tomorrow the
security of our stadium.
>> thank you for your comments.
We thank you.
Welcome to our next speaker my
supervisors joe fitzgerald
rodriguez here not speaking
in my capacity as a standard
reporter but in my capacity as
the PRESIDENT Of the society of
professional journalists
northern california chapter we
defend press freedoms across
northern california and we
promote professional
development with journalists
across the state.
>> we wanted to speak
in support of supervisor melgar
and your good supervisors.
Item number 34 we are really,
really distressed at what
happened at lowell high school.
Think about what they reported
.
I hope you all read the article
that they wrote that started
this whole thing off.
>> the students at lowell high
school did amazing journalism
exposing verbal harassment,
sexual harassment, possible
grooming behavior that they
found at their school.
They did the work of good
journalism and now their
teacher advisor is paying the
price for it.
I got my start at marina middle
school go penguins on our
little broadsheet newspaper
and that is how I got here.
>> that is how I became a
journalist in professional
in san francisco today.
>> what lowell high school did
puts a chill on everything.
Those students are working for
the careers they MAY build to
the lives they MAY build to.
that is really sad.
>> law high school should be
nurturing, nurturing their
talent as journalists and I'm
glad that they're here to hear
this because as empowered by
northern california journalists
I want them to know that
journalism as a profession is
extremely proud of them and you
all should be too.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> all right.
Welcome to our next speaker.
Hello.
Hi everyone.
>> I'll be speaking on behalf
of one of our commissioners.
I'm joshua stafford for the
youth commission.
>> hello, supervisors.
Thank you for giving me the
opportunity to share my
thoughts.
My name is winnie liao and I
serve as the district three
youth commissioner on the S.F.
Youth commission.
But first and foremost I'm a
student at lowell high school.
When I walked down the hallways
of any school and see the words
painted on the walls or printed
on posters telling students to
be kind, communicate with
others or listen to all voices.
I'm not reminded of these
ideals of the breathtaking
irony we are taught to value
critical thinking and to
question to investigate until
we actually do.
The moment as students voice
becomes too loud, too
revealing.
Our educational institutions
suppress rather than support.
>> it speaks volumes about the
ideals that we claim to
champion.
>> trust is something that is
rapidly deteriorating at this
very moment.
According to the pew research
center, young americans are the
least trusting of other people
and key institutions.
And can we blame them when they
have very spaces meant to
nurture independent thought
and become spaces of stifling
and muffling?
What messages are we sending?
>> this isn't about a single
article or a single school or
city.
It's a troubling trend
throughout the bay area and the
nation.
With the current crackdowns on
institutions of higher
education and protection of
student journalism in our high
schools is more important than
ever.
If we want to prepare young
people to inherit and address
the issues of our current world
not to just exist within it but
to critically examine,
challenge and improve it, we
need it to support them.
>> we have to show our
government that our government
is a representation of the
people and that they champion
the qualities and beliefs that
this country is built on.
>> the issues facing our world
climate change, housing
affordability, political
polarization will not be solved
by those who stay silent but by
those who have learned the
courage of speaking truth
especially when it makes those
in power uncomfortable.
By affirming this resolution
S.F. Has the opportunity to do
more than protect student
rights.
You have the chance to
reconstruct trust to
demonstrate that governance is
not about silencing voices but
amplifying them.
Protect the protect their right
to rally and protect their
right to know.
>> thank you.
Thank you, joshua ochoa for
your comments and for that of
the commissioner.
Welcome joy.
>> good afternoon
and supervisors my name is
chosen and I am reading a
comment on behalf of clarice
kim who is the district once
you've commissioner and a
reporter for the richmond
review and sunset beacon papers
but she is primarily speaking
to you today as a proud news
editor of the lincoln log
and she wants to express her
support for the resolution
in support of student
journalism.
She wants to first share a
tradition that they have at the
lincoln log.
It's their editorial planning
process.
Once an issue they spend an
entire class period
brainstorming arguments around
the projector screen.
Last edition their editorial
criticize the school
administration and they have
ran opinions against their
school security bell schedule
and the next year's class cuts.
It's thanks to their first
amendment rights that they get
to defend their stances after
all, their paper has faced
lawsuits scathing letters to
their editors and pushed back
during administration meetings.
But they welcome the
opportunity for discourse they
choose to wield their words
with as much responsibility as
any concord professional
publication would.
Their opinions should be
protected with the same rights
as any adult journalists.
Student journalism allows them
to share their voices
and create an impact on their
communities.
What has happened to the law is
a blatant and concerning
involve ation of their first
amendment rights.
If we start restricting the
freedom of speech of our youth
we are censoring the democracy
of the future.
>> today their paper went to
the press for its final issue
this school year this time
their editorial is on how the
deportation of student
protesters sets a dangerous
precedent for the first
amendment rights commissioner
kim wants to leave you all with
an excerpt from the editorial.
We must speak up now before our
civil liberties are stripped
away and america's identity as
the land of the free and the
brave becomes the land of the
oppressed and silence.
Thank you.
>> thank you joy for bringing
the comments of the
commissioner.
>> next speaker please.
>> good evening.
Board of supervisors and acting
PRESIDENT Walton.
My name is richard steve
peterson and I'm here to speak
a little bit about why I'm
dressed this way.
I'm in a $1,200 suit and $60
tie and $300 shoes and now I'm
kind of like one of you.
>> problem is the suit has
holes in it from moss and the
shoes are have a hole in it to
.
But that's not really why I
came to speak with you and make
an impression.
>> but I was shocked.
>> shocked.
I tell you last week during
chief chief scott's plea to
extend the budget.
A man came in with a so-called
ankle bracelet that he would
throw up on the thing.
I have little tassels, some
nice $300 shoes.
>> and then as he was walking
out the first time he shouted
these anti-semitic statements.
>> and somehow you were able to
forgive him and hear him a
second time.
And even then he claimed to be
a man of GOD.
And I here am also I guess a
man of GOD or dog or whatever.
>> and I want to leave the car
that I wanted to give which are
the hebrew alphabet the ones
that I tried to send to up to
you.
I have 12 copies one for each
supervisor, one for the one for
the clerk and I like to enter
them into the record.
And I want to do a shout out
for a friend today the
frenchman.
I can't remember how to
pronounce his last name.
And he thank you.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> thank you.
Well, thank you.
thank you.
What are the supervisors?
Good evening.
I just want to elaborate on I'm
queen vanessa bates.
I'm a born native of her point.
And I just want to elaborate on
supervisor walton comment about
the san francisco park alliance
.
As a founding member of friends
of young black carmen, the
experience with san francisco
park alliance was very, very
stressful.
And they didn't do what they
said they was going to do at
night when they came into our
communities to help build our
parks up and keep families
and youth inside the parks.
>> so our really liked to see
this san francisco park
alliance and they scrutinizing
in a way undermining
and mismanaging funds get dealt
with just like the charges
dealt with the dreamscape of
initiative removing funds
and doing everything you did
for us.
I would really like to see that
happen to the san francisco
park alliance.
And now that I know that my
district supervisor is on it,
we're going to make sure as
community we stay with him on
this because san francisco park
alliance by them not working
with us in community it keeps
us like someone like myself
from bringing youth inside the
parks in doing great things for
our youth and it's at the times
when budgets is getting cuts
and young people need to be
engaged to be in the parks to
stay safe.
This is not a good time for
people like park alliance to be
undermined in the community
and not doing what they said it
was supposed to do.
So I appreciate of your stay on
them and hold them accountable
like I do everybody else.
Thank you for your comments.
It's it's welcome our next
speaker go.
>> good afternoon.
My name is mary trammel and I
live in district ten.
>> a few years ago I had to
file a charge against the human
rights commission for getting
rid of me after I came back off
a sick leave.
The suit has been settled
in DECEMBER.
I haven't heard nothing from
the city attorney's office
and I would like to ask this
board if they can assign
somebody to help me guide me
through that process because I
don't even know what I'm
waiting for.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
In just a moment one of my
staff members will come over
and obtain your information.
So if you wouldn't mind sitting
right there in the front, are
there any other members of the
public who would like to
address the board during
general public comment?
>> okay.
MR. PRESIDENT.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
As you know, the speaker's
public comment is now closed
and let us go back to item
number 19.
And I see we have
representatives from the
department of public works.
>> I would say hi.
>> so we are back with our
final list.
We have a copy for each board
member and just to let everyone
know that we were able to waive
three properties in the hallway
.
>> thank you so much.
>> and with the 33 waive the
rest were agreements by
property owners.
>> yes.
The rest of the list will have
a property line.
>> I thank you so much.
But colleagues, my first
question is can we accept the
amendments that have been made
by the department?
I don't see any objection to
that.
So we will accept the
amendments to the properties
identified by dpw staff without
objection.
>> and MADAM Clerk, can you
please call the roll on
resolution with the amended
report on item 19 to accept the
amended report from department
of public works supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
melgar I melgar I supervisor
sadr sadr eyes supervisor
cheryl cheryl I supervisor
walton I walton I supervisor
chin chin I supervisor chin
chin I supervisor dorsey dorsey
I and supervisor and engardio
in guardian I there are ten I
thank you and without
objection.
>> item 19 is adopted with the
amended report.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you MADAM Clerk let's go
to her for adoption without
committee reference.
yes we have items 30 through 37
which were introduced for
adoption without committee
reference.
A unanimous vote is required
for adoption of a resolution on
first reading today.
Alternatively, a member MAY
require a resolution on first
reading to go to committee.
>> thank you supervisor melgar
I'd like to set for item 34
please.
Thank you.
>> I don't see any other items
or anyone else on the roster.
So MADAM Clerk can we vote on
items 3031, 32, 33, 3536 and 37
?
>> yes, MR. PRESIDENT.
On items 3031, 32, 33, 35, 36
and 37 supervisor fielder
fielder eyes supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
and supervisor and engardio
and engardio I there are ten
I's thank you without objection
these resolutions are passed
unanimously.
>> MADAM Clerk would you please
call item number 34?
>> item 34 this is a resolution
to support student journalism
to affirm the importance of
free press and to uphold free
speech.
>> thank you supervisor melgar.
Thank you very much, PRESIDENT
Walton.
First I'd like to thank
supervisor in gado himself a
journalist for working with me
on this resolution along with
our co-sponsors supervisor
fielder chen cheryl sadr,
mahmood walton and dorsey.
>> this resolution is about
defending student journalism
and the right to a free press.
Very few times in my lifetime
has been as important to do
that as right now given what we
are going through as a nation.
I want to thank the journalist
and the residents who have
reached out to show support for
the student editorial board at
lowell high school and at other
schools.
Do you know that they fund the
printing of the lowell
themselves?
They sell cookies in addition
to groundbreaking journalism
in writing.
While it might not have been
the intention of the
administration to leave
students feeling intimidated
with their request to approve
future applications and the
sudden reassignment of their
teachers who advised them the
impact matters and it has a
reverberating effect.
Today we received a response
from the san francisco unified
school district and while I
appreciate that they are paying
close attention to this issue,
this really isn't about the
teacher reassignment process.
It is about how students
journalists are being treated
in a demand to the S.F. Usc to
develop and implement
consistent policies
and procedures compliant with
the law.
In that respect the rights of
student journalist I implore
them to go even further than
that in providing training
and guidance to their staff so
that student publications are
supported in full.
I am so incredibly proud of the
courageous student journalists
their teacher, the editorial
board of the lowell the student
newspaper for taking a stand
in the face of intimidation.
As I discussed last week while
our constitu mission is being
undermined, we must forcefully
support the right to free
speech.
>> these student journalists
remind us that without a free
press we the people lose a
vital avenue by which we can
speak truth to power.
Thank you colleagues for your
support.
>> thank you.
Supervisor male ga supervisor
and gaudio thank you supervisor
melgar for bringing this to our
attention.
As you said I worked many years
as a journalist before I became
a politician.
I was even the editor of my
high school newspaper and I
have to tell you back in the
late 1980s and early 90s we
wrote some controversial
stories at a time when life was
very different back then and we
wrote about the only gay bar
in our town.
We wrote about date rape topics
that were very, very taboo
especially 35 years ago.
So it can be done right.
High schools can produce good
journalism that challenges
teachers and the district
and abides by free speech.
We did it 35 years ago and we
can do it today.
And even I do want to call out
in the sunset district at
lincoln high school.
lincoln log is a is a wonderful
publication and if you look at
the issue the most recent issue
they have a very challenging
article that challenges the
school district and their
budget decisions.
So it's doable and I think we
should all support student
journalists and ensure that the
first amendment is upheld.
>> thank you.
Thank you, supervisor
and guardian supervisor
mahmood.
>> I just want to thank
supervisor melgar again for
introducing this resolution
and to the students at law
who've been standing up in the
face of this this this backlash
from the district.
>> I was also editor in chief
of my first my high school's
first online newspaper and I
just wanted to actually mention
that this morning I got a
message from my old high school
advisor who knew that you had
authored this resolution
and this is all the way down
in palo alto.
And so the actions that you've
introduced here today
in defense of the student
journalists at law are already
being recognized across the bay
area by other high school
journalism programs because I
feel they also recognize how
important it is to uplift
and stand up for student
journalists.
And so I appreciate and commend
again you introducing this
resolution.
It is important happening both
what's happening locally
and nationally as well.
>> thank you.
supervisor mahmood supervisor
fielder thank you.
>> yes, thank you supervisor
melgar for introducing this
leading the resolution.
Thanks to all the co sponsors
but most importantly thank you
so much to the youth for coming
out all the way to city hall on
a school day.
It is a testament to your
courage and your strength
and I'm just so so thankful for
for you and the community for
supporting you.
>> thanks so much.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder and I would
just say that I echo the
sentiments and comments from my
colleagues.
>> and with that we will take
this resolution.
>> same house, same call
and this resolution shall be
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, do we have any
imperative agenda items today?
I have none to report.
MR. PRESIDENT, I believe there
are no in memoriam.
That is correct.
But colleagues, this brings us
to the end of our agenda and we
are adjourned.
>> this